<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Bartholmew fairing for parentes to bestow vpon their sonnes and daughters, and for one friend to giue vnto another: shevving that children are not to marie, without the consent of their parentes, in whose povver and choise it lieth to prouide wiues and husbandes for their sonnes and daughters. Wherin is sufficiently prooued, what in this point is the office of the fathers and in like maner declared the part and duty of all obedient children. By Iohn Stockvvood, minister and preacher of Tunbridge.</title>
            <author>Stockwood, John, d. 1610.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105880</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841606</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841606</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6202</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12984)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6202)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1611:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Bartholmew fairing for parentes to bestow vpon their sonnes and daughters, and for one friend to giue vnto another: shevving that children are not to marie, without the consent of their parentes, in whose povver and choise it lieth to prouide wiues and husbandes for their sonnes and daughters. Wherin is sufficiently prooued, what in this point is the office of the fathers and in like maner declared the part and duty of all obedient children. By Iohn Stockvvood, minister and preacher of Tunbridge.</title>
                  <author>Stockwood, John, d. 1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 91 [i.e. 93] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, for Iohn Harrison the younger, dwelling in pater Noster-rowe, at the signe of the golden Anchor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 96 repeated in number only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Religious aspects --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Bartholmew Fairing for Parentes, to beſtow vpon their ſonnes and daughters, and for one friend to giue vnto another: Shevving that children are not to marie, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of their parentes, in whoſe povver and choiſe it lieth to prouide wiues and husbandes for their ſonnes and daughters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherin is ſufficiently prooued, what in this point is the office of the fathers and in like maner declared the part and duty of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Iohn Stockwood, Miniſter and preacher of Tunbridge.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 29.6.</bibl>
               <p>Take you wiues, and beget ſonnes and daughters, and take wiues for your ſons, and giue your daughters to husbandes, that they may beare ſons &amp; daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that you may be increaſed there, and not dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, for Iohn Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon the yonger, dwelling in Pater Noſter-rowe, at the ſigne of the golden Anchor.</hi> 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull, M. Thomas Skeuington of Skeuington, Eſquire, at this preſent high Sheriffe of Leiceſter-ſhire and one of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Maieſties Iuſtices of the peace there: Iohn Stockewood Miniſter and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the worde of God at Tunbridge in Kent, wiſheth all felicitie of mind and bodie, through Ieſus Chriſt our moſt merciful redeemer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hildren (right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) as we al wel know, when their parentes or any of thoſe, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue any familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, goe vnto any faire, vſe commonly at their taking their iourney to ſay vnto them: <hi>I pray you bring me home a Fayring.</hi> And not only children are for the moſt part thus affected, but we ſee it alſo to be the faſhion of others of greater grouth, &amp; further yeares, when as at faires they meete with their friendes and acquaintance, to bee begging and asking of them: <hi>What will you giue me for a fairing?</hi> And the curteſie that is this way beſtowed, be it in a maner neuer ſo ſmall and ſimple, is notwithſtanding wel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and kindly taken from the hand of the giuer, as being a ſigne and token of his good will and louing affection towardes the party, on whom he doth beſtowe the ſame. This
<pb facs="tcp:6202:3"/>cuſtome ſimply in it ſelfe not to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (although through abuſe the beſt thinges may be peruerted) I haue at this preſent fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my ſelf vnto, &amp; as I could for the ſhortnes of the time, prepared this treatiſe, diſcourſing vpon the office of parentes in prouiding their children of honeſt mariages in due ſeaſon, &amp; ſhewing at large the dutie and obedience of their ſonnes and daughters in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>How neceſſarie for al ſortes of people this my trauaile (ſuch as it is) may be, it is not my meaning here in many wordes to dilate. The generall want of performance of dutie in this reſpect, on the one ſide by the parentes, and on the other by their children, hath bin the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-nurſe, &amp; brood-mother of many great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences, wherwith both the Church &amp; common wealth, yea and many priuate fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, are not a litle peſtered, againſt the which if by this my labour, God of his mercie gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto it this bleſsing, I may be thought to haue ſet downe ſome remedie, it ſhal no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing greeue me to haue taken the ſame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glad if any way by my ſimple ſeruice, I can bring any profite vno the Church of God, the which howe much or how litle ſoeuer it bee, who ſo ſhall thereby receiue any benefit next vnto God he ſhall be beholding vnto your worſhip for the ſame, who haue bene the chiefe occaſion of the publiſhing hereof.</p>
            <p>For owing a dutie vnto you for your cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie ſhewed, at the requeſt of the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable,
<pb facs="tcp:6202:3"/>the Earle of Huntington, my verie ſingular good Lord and maiſter, I haue euer ſince bene deuiſing, how I might giue out ſome teſtimonie of my gratefull remembrance of this worſhipful kindnes, and hauing none other meanes of greater valour, I haue preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to giue trial therof by theſe paper thanks whereby al poſteritie may witneſſe, that I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelfe to remaine a debtor vnto you for vndeſerued curteſie extended to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, the which, in aſmuch as I am able no other waies to requite, I do in al humilitie requeſt your worſhip to account and reckon me in the number of thoſe, who being manie pleaſured by you, though hindmoſt peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in worldlie abilitie, will be found not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding as forward as the formoſt in all dutifull and thankfull good will, as one that hateth in the worlde nothing more than the moſt vglie and loathſome monſter of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and vnthankfulnes. The time falling out ſo fitlie with the finiſhing of this worke, and publiſhing the ſame, I haue geuen vnto it the name of a <hi>Bartholmew Fayring,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The reaſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Title.</note> the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the noueltie of the title to drawe on the multitude of people that nowe out of all places of our country repaire vnto the citie, to the better beholding and conſideration of the matter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the treatiſe: the which, as it is general, and concerneth all that either are, or may be parents, or children: ſo the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine marked heedfullie, and practiſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly,
<pb facs="tcp:6202:4"/>ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not chooſe but fal out auaillable vnto manie, who learning here, that which for the moſt part they were ignorant of, and thought ſtrange before, will henceforth prooue to be more carefull fathers in proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding chriſtian mariages for their ſonnes and daughters, and their children more dutifull &amp; obedient in being ruled by them, &amp; follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their choice, and in diligent wareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that they intangle and bewrap not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in wedlocke-bands without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and liking of their parents. Accept ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you (right worſhipfull) this ſimple preſent as an vnfeined token of my good will, with that fauourable curteſie, wherewith you are woont to imbrace others much bounden welwillers, the which, if you ſhall vouchſafe me, I haue obtained my deſire praying the almighty for euer to protect you. Tunbridge, this 20 Auguſt. 1589.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your W. much bounden in al dutifull and moſt thankful good will: <hi>Iohn Stockwood.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:4"/>
            <head>To all godlie Parentes, with their like vertuous children, and all other the Chriſtian Readers, into whoſe handes this book may come, increaſe of true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; ſincere practiſe of the ſame through Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not for nothing (right curteous and christian rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders) that we haue bene by our Sauiour Chriſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares ſithens before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand warned of the ſtate and condition of this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and doting world ſet on fire vpon miſchiefe &amp; iniquitie, that the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer it groweth and haſteneth vnto his end, the worſe &amp; worſe it ſhal daily wax, inſomuch that the Lord when he ſhal come to iudgement,<note place="margin">Luk. <hi>18.8.</hi>
               </note> ſhall hardlie finde faith vpon the earth. For ſuch are the miſeries of our times, that notwithſtanding the plentifull preaching of the Goſpell in moſt places, ſin ſtill raigneth in aboundance, and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie getteth more and more the vpper-hand, inſomuch that thoſe enormities and outrages, the which are condemned by the law of Nature, the word of God, the practiſe of the godlie in all ages, the teſtimony of the Heathen, and generall conſent of all commendable learning, are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding of many not onely laughed and ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted as, but alſo ſought to be countenanced, and
<pb facs="tcp:6202:5"/>defended (aneuident token of the great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our age) of ſuch as otherwiſe want not their due praiſe for ciusll conuerſation and beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. Among theſe is not the laſt nor least, the too vſuall bad cuſtome of childrens marrieng, without the conſent and allowance of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes a ſinne that nature it ſelfe abborreth, and all writers of the better note, in all ages vtterlie diſalowed, and yet of the greater number holden and taken for no fault at all, whoſe error in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ariſing for the most part of ignorance, I haue fasthfully laboured by all ſufficsent kind of proofes in this writing to diſprooue, the which not vnfitly, nor nigh my purpoſe and meaning at the leaſtwiſe) offenſiuely, I haue tearmed a <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholmew fairing,</hi> reſpecting the time, and the great reſort that yearly come vp to the fair, who, now if they liſt may haue a nouell of ſmall prices but yet of much value, to beſtow vpon themſelues their children &amp; their friends, worthy I hope of their reading and much more of their practiſe, as their ſeueral places &amp; callings ſhall require. And I haue bene the more willing to enter into this courſe, and vndersaken this matter, that I might diſcharge ſome part of a promiſe vnto diuerſe my godly friends of Kent and Suſſex, which are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the right honourable and vertuous Earle of Huntington, vnto whom I alſo my ſelfe am bound in all dutifulnes in the Lord, who by their due right may iuſtly claim the ſame as my hand of whom they haue all ſo well deſerued, and vnto whom I am ſure this treatiſe will come welcome
<pb facs="tcp:6202:5"/>Howſoeuer it fall out of ſome to be miſliked: for concerning them I am fully perſuaded, as Ioſhua ſpeaketh of himſelfe and his.<note place="margin">Ioſhua. 24.16</note> 
               <hi>That they and their houſes will ſerue the Lord.</hi> And I make no doubt of alother zealous Chriſtians, but that this labour ſhall be well thought off. It is growen I conſeſse, albeit vnto no great, yet much bigger bulke, then when I began it, I ſuppoſed it ſhould: the Lord hauing giuen a further bleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing vnto it then I looked for, whereby I am comforted, that he will of lake mercie direct it vnto the good and benefit of his Church. Eloquence and rethoricall floriſhings, with filed wordes and braue phraſes, are not here to be expected and looked for, as bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch flowers, the which neuer grewe in my barren, plaine, and homely country garden, yet may the hearbs that here are to be found, though not carrieng any outward gay and gallant ſhew, yeeld an wholſome and pleaſant ſmell in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrels of all godly parents, worn not in the hands, but in the hearts and minds of all louing and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull children, the which ſhould henceforth of conſcience and knowledge put into diligent vſe and practiſe this most neceſſarie and waightie point of dutie, the which hither to of ignorance, and lacke of teaching, hath of the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber bene neglected, foreſlowed, and ouerpaſſed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Vnfeignedlie wiſhing your knowledge and practiſe of all neceſſarie duties.</hi> Iohn Stockwood.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>That Mariages are not</hi> to be made without the conſent of <hi>Parentes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong many other vices, wherewith the worlde at this day is full fraugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, inſomuch that the verie elements themſelues, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the reſt of the creatures (as S. Paule in his 8 Cap.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20.21.22.23.</note> vnto the Romans doth teach vs) doe groane vnder the burthen of them, looking for a change, from the vanitie whereunto they are made ſubiect through the ſinne of man, that they may be reſtored vnto the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the ſonnes of God, this one is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the leaſt nor the laſt, whereby youth for the moſt part is growne vnto ſuch a paſſe, that forgetting al childlike affection and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull obedience vnto father and mother in the higheſt point of ſubiection, the which they owe vnto them in this life, and whervp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dependeth their making or marring (as they ſay) together with the continuall ioy or ſorrow of their parentes they whollie follow
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6202:7"/>their own will and let out the raines vnto their owne vnbrideled &amp; vnſetled luſts, making matches according to their own fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle fantaſies, and chooſing vnto themſelues yokefellowes after the outward deceiuable direction of the eie, nothing regarding the ſounde aduice of a minde guided with the knowledge &amp; feare of God, the which coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelleth to reſpect the inwarde graces and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namentes of the ſoule, &amp; not to be enamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the outward garniſhing, beauty, br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uerie and decking of the bodie. And here of it commeth to paſſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.1.</note> that men in their maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges following the maners of the ſons of the firſt forlorne world, ſeeing the daughters of men to be beautifull &amp; pleaſing vnto the eie, take vnto themſelues of all that they like, not waiting nor ſtaieng for the choiſe of their parents, by whoſe authoritie, if they ought to be directed in the matters of ſmaller waight and leſſe importance,<note place="margin">If obedience due vnto pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the ſmalleſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, much more in the greater.</note> as now is ſo ſhameleſſe and void of grace, that he dare to denie, how much more are they then to be ruled by their graue aduice in this which chiefly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Gods glorie, their owne welfare, the chearing and reioicing of them that haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten them.</p>
            <p>But like as in the firſt age of the world, this ſin is in the place of Geneſis before recited, reckoned vp by the holie Ghoſt for one of the principall cauſes that mooued God to ſet wide open the windowes of heauen, and to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6202:7"/>poure downe raine in ſuch fearfull aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, as that in the raging force &amp; ſwelling ſtreame of the ſame, man with all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures miſerably periſhed, thoſe onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the which were preſerued in the Arke ſo queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>les we do owe moſt of the plagues, wherewith now a daies God puniſheth this preſent age, and in the end will in fearfull maner conſume the ſame vnto this great and maine ſin of children their matching in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage without the counſaile and aduice, nay ſpite of the teeth of their godly parentes. For mariage being the meanes the which God himſelfe hath ordained and ſanctified for the propagation and increaſe of mankind, that being taken in hand in his feare, a godly ſeed being multiplied &amp; growen vp here on earth the ſame may be bleſſed to the conſtitution &amp; making of a Church, the which may ſerue him in holines and righteouſnes: when the ſame is taken in hand with the breach of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, ſo far off is it, that any bleſsing is to be hoped for, that contrariwiſe his hot indignation and heauie curſe hangeth ouer that houſe &amp; familie,<note place="margin">Mariage ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand with the breach of God. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, can not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> wher the parties which are the principall pillers and vpholders of the ſame, are linked andtied together in ſuch a ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of wedlock, whoſe links &amp; incloſings are not faſtened and coupled together with the neceſſarie and lawfull aſſent and liking of the parentes, whoſe authoritie &amp; conſent ought to beare the chiefeſt ſway, and ſtrike likewiſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6202:8"/>the greateſt ſtroke in this moſt holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie action. And like as mariage is begon &amp; enterpriſed in the feare of God according to his word, there God is well pleaſed, there the parties ſo matched liue together in a ioyfull agreement and liking the one of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there God is honoured and ſerued in ſynceritie and truth, there the children, when God giueth them, with the reſt of the familie are inſtructed and brought vp in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of religion, and grounds of faith: ſo on the other ſide, the regard of that which God eſpecially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth, being ſhut out of our mariages, there muſt needes enſue his diſlike, and diſpleaſure, there is iar and diſcord, there Gods honour is neglected, there houſhold-diſcipline and chriſtian-inſtruction of ſuch as belong vnto our chardge, goeth vtterly to wracke, and is nothing at all regarded. And no marueil: for, if where God bleſſeth, all thinges goe well and doe proſper, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentlie where he curſeth, there nothing thriueth, hath good ſucceſſe, or goeth happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forward.</p>
            <p>Now if anie ſhall ſuppoſe that theſe ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are but wordes of courſe, &amp; carrie a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant ſhew, without any ſubſtance or proofe of matter, pointing rather vnto ſuch an order as we would haue, or wiſh to be obſerued in the matches of our children, then ſhewing by good euidence that ſo it ought indeed and of right to be, it is now time that we drawe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6202:8"/>ſomewhat neerer vnto the queſtion, the which vpon waightie conſideration we haue taken in hand,<note place="margin">The principal drift and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of this Treatiſe.</note> &amp; by Gods aſsiſtance mean to prooue: which is, that children may not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry without the conſent &amp; agreement of their parentes. And this I hope ſhall in ſuch ſort be performed, as that it ſhall plainlie appeare, that not only the conſent of father &amp; mother is chieflie requiſite in the caſe of mariage, but alſo in the former ages and more ancient times of this world, alwaies declining from better to worſe, that the choiſe it ſelfe of wiues for the ſonnes, and husbandes for the daughters, reſted wholly in the power &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the parentes, inſomuch that not onely the better ſort of the children of the godlie referred the whole care of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing this way vnto the prouident electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their fathers and mothers, but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie heathen themſelues that were not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſt grace, and had cleane ſhaken of the yoke of dutiful obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, would not ſo much as once vouchſafe to heare of the motion of any match for themſelues in the ſtate of wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock, except the choiſe of their fathers &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had gon before.</p>
            <p>Firſt then I willay this down for the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, whereupon the reſt of the building ſhall be framed, the which is granted and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon among all the learned: namelie, that howſoeuer the minde of man ſince and through the fall of our firſt parentes, is blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6202:9"/>and darkened,<note place="margin">God hath planted cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine generall principles, &amp; groundes of true thin the hearts of all men.</note> yet God hath left ſome ſmal &amp; general ſparkles of light in the ſame, the which the verie heathen haue acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, and receiued for vndoubted trueths, and there is none ſo blunt and ſhameles, that he can gaine ſay them, as for example: <hi>That we ought not to hurt or wrong any man: That we muſt giue to euery one that which is his.</hi> And (which is the head and chiefe of all, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our outward behauiour, and ſuch dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges as vſuallie doe fall out betweene man and man) <hi>Doe not that vnto another, the which thou wouldest not haue to be done vnto thy ſelfe.</hi> with many other ſuch like, the which we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe tearme The law of nature, or of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, be cauſe they are naturallie engrauen and written in the heartes of all men,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.13.</note> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued and receiued with the generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all nations, yea and that ſo far foorth, that thoſe which do violate and breake them were worthy of death, as the bolie Apoſtle himſelfe ſomewhere in wordes doeth teſtifie and witneſſe: if therfore it be a principle that no man doubteth of, <hi>That we ſhould doe as we would be done vnto,</hi> and that we ought not to doe vnto others that thing, the like wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we would be greeued and offended, they ſhould doe vnto vs:<note place="margin">The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the law of nature</note> I appeale to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all graceleſſe ſonnes and daughters, as now a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aies (the more is the pitie) in too great multitudes betroth themſelues in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage without the priuitie, nay againſt the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6202:9"/>will of their fathers and mother, whether that they would take it in good part at the hands of their children, if they ſhould in like maner prouide themſelues of wiues and husbands, their good wil and conſent being not firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained before, if there bee none hauing any conſcience at all, but that the ſame dulie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined euerie night when he goeth vnto his bed, telleth him that he woulde not thus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe be ſerued: let this rule then be ſufficient to teach him, that he alſo ought not to marie without the well liking and agreement of his father and mother. Wouldeſt not thou what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou art, that thy childe, if thou carrie any fatherly mind towards him, ſhould in his matching and marrieng be aduiſed and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by thee? And dareſt thou affiance and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelfe vnto an other in the moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and holie eſtate of mariage, without the knowledge and counſell of thy father? Thou thy ſelfe the more dearly and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thou loueſt thine owne childe, the more deeplie wilt thou bee touched with griefe and ſorrowe in thy verie innermoſt bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and affections, he, if he beſtowe himſelfe contrarie to thy liking, and can thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat thee, thinkeſt thou, reioice and bee glad, when thou haſt wedded contrarie vnto their mind and good liking? Doe therefore as thou wouldeſt be done vnto: Marie with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of thy parentes, as thou wouldeſt that thy children ſhould doe with thine. And as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6202:10"/>thou wouldeſt not that thoſe vnder thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment ſhould ioin in matrimonie againſt thy will, ſo in any caſe take heed, that thou contract not thy ſelf according to thine own pleaſure, but ſtay for the direction and good aduice of thy father, for it is an hard matter to haue the teſtimonie of thine owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to bee alwaies accuſing thee that thou haſt done amiſſe, and contrarie vnto that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, the which thou oweſt vnto thy ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, and lookeſt alſo that thy children ſhould performe vnto thee.</p>
            <p>Secondlie, that theſe priuie contracts, that is to ſay,<note place="margin">The ſecond reaſon taken from the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ouer their children</note> ſuch as are made in ſecret, or in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or otherwiſe in place neuer ſo publique without the conſent of the parents, are not lawful, may this way more plainly appeare, if we weigh &amp; conſider, that children are not at their owne libertie, &amp; diſpoſition, nor (as they ſay) their owne-men, but vnder the authority and power of their parentes, like as ſeruantes are at the diſpoſing of their maiſters. Nay they are ſo much more bound vnto their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers &amp; mothers then ſeruants are, or can be vnder the power of their maiſters, by howe much next vnder God, they do ovve their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie being vnto thoſe that begat them, vvhich they doe not vnto their maiſters, &amp; therefore is the band of their obedience greater and ſtraighter vnto their fathers, then is that of ſeruants vnto their maiſters. Here of it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that thoſe vvhich are alike ſubiect vnto
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6202:10"/>the gouernment of others, are alſo alike de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from the ſame freedoms &amp; liberties, that otherwiſe, if they were not thus ſubiect, they might enioy: but ſeruants and children are tied with a like and equall band of ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction inſomuch that if in this behalfe ther be any ods, it is in this, that children owe more dutie vnto their fathers then ſeruantes vnto their maiſters, as was prooued a litle before: they are therefore debarred from the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie and freedome, whereof enſueth, that if ſeruantes haue not this libertie without the leaue of their maiſters to betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto others, no more may children without the authoritie of their parentes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance and betroth themſelues in mariage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others: but ſeruants are by the lawes, as the learned doe knowe (and I ſpeake of the lawes and ſeruants,<note place="margin">The lawes of elder times re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrain ſeruants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o liberty at their owne pleaſure to be take them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers without the leaue of their maiſters.</note> not as they are with vs at this day, but as they were in the more ancient and elder times) reſtrained of this libertie to place themſelues with others againſt the will of their maiſters, therefore children may not giue themſelues in matrimonie vnto others without the conſent of their progenitors. And albeit that by the lawes of our own land nowe in force there bee as yet no prouiſo made againſt the matching of ſeruants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the approbation and allowance of their maiſters, yet (vnder the correction of others) it ſeemeth vnto me great reaſon, that where there are no parents, euen in thoſe places the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6202:11"/>ſeruants, ſhould take the direction of their godly maiſters in this behalfe, in vvhich my iudgement I am not ſingular, but can, if need be auouch mine aſſertion by the authoritie of the learned But what ſhall this neede, when as the equitie here of may bee inferred of that which we read in the books of Moſes, where, ſuch as pleaſe with diligence to conferre the places,<note place="margin">Exod. 21. Leuit. 25. Deut. 15.12.</note> they may eaſily find, that ſuch ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te as were Ebrues, though the time of their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice was ſhorter then was theirs, which were ſtrangers and of other nations, yet during the ſpace of their yeares they had to ſerue in, they were not to marie at their owne libertie, but their maiſters hand bare the chiefe ſtroke in this buſines. This courſe beeing obſerued in the Ebrue ſeruants, it will not, as I take it be gain-ſaid, that ſeruants of other people and countries, whoſe bondage in manie reſpects was far heauier, were likewiſe depriued of this libertie of marrying, during the time of their ſeruitude and thraldom, without the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of their Lordes and maiſters: yet hereby is not meant to preiudicate or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach, much leſſe to controlle the libertie of our lawes, or law-makers, in ſuch caſes as God hath left free vnto them, but onely out of that which God himſelfe ſet downe vnto his owne people in debarring ſeruants, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to make their owne choiſe in caſes of mariage, to prooue that children, which are in as great or rather greater ſubiection vnto
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6202:11"/>their fathers authority, are likewiſe bound by as hard a band to tarie for the conſent of their parentes in their contractes of matrimonie.</p>
            <p>Thirdlie, the great ſoueraintie,<note place="margin">The third rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the large iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rildiction and power the which in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times hath bin per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto parentes ouer their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the which cuſtome, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit that it be not ſimply to to be allowed yet it proos ueth their for ueraintie in other matters to be wel per lourmed by their children without any inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> rule &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that by the law of Moſes was giuen vnto the Iewiſh fathers ouer their children, and by the ordinances of the Romanes to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ouer their ſonnes and daughters, by vertue whereof the one in caſes of neceſsitie might ſel their children for bondſlaues to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue themſelues, and the other might kill them in reuenge of their owne priuate iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done vnto themſelues, or publique e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities offered vnto others, albeit that of Moſes may be thought to be permitted, like as other thinges for a time in regard of the hardneſſe of their heart, and this of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes deſerue iuſtlie to bee condemned as barbarous, cruell, and ſauage, yet doe they both argue, that if parents authoritie were in thoſe times ſo large in thinges that ſeeme ſo hardlie to be digeſted, that they had a far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter authoritie in thoſe matters &amp; duties, the which might be performed with more conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and much leſſe difficultie and danger, namelie in bearing chiefeſt ſway in the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of their children, and in other cauſes of like dutifull obedience.<note place="margin">The fourth reaſon from the condition of goods vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the power that the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſame</note>
            </p>
            <p>To this may be added, that the children are worthelie to be reckoned among the goodes and ſubſtance of their fathers, and that by a more eſpeciall right then any thing els, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6202:12"/>the which belongeth vnto their poſſeſsion, as thoſe which are more neerlie linked and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto them, and which coſt them more dearlie, being fleſh of their fleſh, and bone of their bone, and without whom, they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bone: ſo that they owe themſelues whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnto them in all maner of obedience and dutifull affection, and ſhall in ſeeking to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troth themſelues at their owne pleaſures, not regarding to haue the good will and leaue of their parentes, deale as prepoſterouſlie, and ouerthwattlie, as if the goodes ſhould goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to diſpoſe the owner and poſſeſſor of the ſame, and not be diſpoſed and ordered by thoſe vnto whom the poſſeſsion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of the ſame doeth by right and equitie belong and appertaine: for it ſtandeth with great reaſon, that the owner diſpoſe of the goodes, and not contrariwiſe the goodes of the owner, which were in deed a thing verie abſurd or contrarie to all reaſon. Now if any ſhall doubt,<note place="margin">Children are the goodes of the parents.</note> whether that the children bee to be reckoned among the goodes of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes or no, he ſeemeth to bee ignorant of that point the which the deuill himſelfe well enough vnderſtood, as we may reade in the firſt of Iob, where it is ſet downe, that when God gaue him leaue to deale withal that Iob had, he medleth with his ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as well as with his ſeruants, and reſt of his ſubſtance taking them alſo to be a portion of the ſame. Wherefore euen in this that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6202:12"/>are their fathers riches (as it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaying) they muſt not beſtow themſelues but muſt be beſtowed of their parents, whoſe goods they are. And leaſt any man ſhoulde contemne this as a weake and childiſh reaſon let him know, that the learned Father Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Beza vſeth it, although not in the ſame iuſt number of wordes, yet in this verie ſelfe ſame argument, and to the ſelfe ſame purpoſe, in his booke <hi>de repudijs &amp; diuortijs,</hi> where his iudgement may bee further ſeene to iumpe with mine fullie in this queſtion, as mine alſo in this behalfe agreeth with the opinion of al the learned.</p>
            <p>And it ſeemeth not to bee much imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent from this place,<note place="margin">The fift rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the vneffectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of vowes without the conſent of parents, and husbands in their childr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and wiues.</note> the which wee read in the booke of Numbers concerning Vowes, where among other things we doe finde, that the vowes which were made by the children without the priuitie and conſent of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and of the wiues without the liking and allowance of their husbandes were altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlawfull and of no force. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon according to true meaning of the place, is geuen by the beſt Interpreters, becauſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther children, nor wines are <hi>ſus iur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> that is, at their owne libertie and appointment, but vnder the rule and gouernment of others, namelie of their parentes and husbands. As therefore to make a vow vnto the Lord, being in it ſelfe and of it owne nature an holy and acceptable action vnto God, and where with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6202:13"/>he is well pleaſed, is notwithſtanding in children vnlawfull, becauſe it is ſuch an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as they onlie may performe which are free and at their owne diſpoſition, the which they are not: ſo in like maner to conſent in matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, although in it ſelfe it be both honeſt &amp; lawfull, yet is it not an action of force in chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, without the conſent and allowance of their parentes, becauſe that children are not free &amp; at their own libertie, but by the lawes both of God and man tied and bound vnto the ſubiection of their fathers, as hath at large bene ſhewed before, and through the whole diſcourſe of this treatiſe is to be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued alſo hereafter.</p>
            <p>In the 22.<note place="margin">The ſixt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the lawes in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus, of enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing of maids, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſelling their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</note> of Exodus there is a law concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the intiſing of maids (a practiſe this day too common, becauſe there is not diſcipline ſharpe enough miniſtred to repreſſe it) and in the chapter before going there is another co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution as touching fathers, that to releeue their owne neceſsities are conſtrained to ſell their daughters for ſeruants: by the firſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it appeareth, that the contract of children without the conſent of their parentes, is not auaillable, or of anie force: and by the ſecond may eaſilie be gathered that ſeruats were not at libertie to make their owne choiſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, but that the right thereof appertained vnto their maiſters, both places iointlie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding flatlie for me, that both children &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants as <hi>Res domenorum:</hi> that is, the goodes of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6202:13"/>their owners, are not, as in other caſes of leſſe waight, ſo in like ſort in that matter of greate importance, namely the beſtowing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in wedlocke for to follow the violent ſtreame of their owne pleaſing affections, but to be ordered and guided by the rule of their fathers and maiſters. I will ſet downe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall wordes of the law in both theſe caſes, that being diligentlie obſerued and marked, fathers and maiſters may learne what was the authoritie in the mariage of their children &amp; ſeruants, and that theſe likewiſe may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what is their part &amp; dutie in theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations.<note place="margin">Exodus. 22.16.17</note> The wordes for intiſing of maides are theſe: <hi>And if a man intiſe a maid that is not betrethed, and lie with her, he ſhall endow her and take her to wife: if her father refuſe to giue her to him, he ſhall pay money according to the dowrie of virgins.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 21.7.8.9.</note> Here is expreſlie ſet downe, that albeit the two parties were fullie agreed, yet is the match not to goe forwarde, vnleſſe the father alſo doe giue his conſent. Now for the father his ſelling of his daughter, to redeeme his owne need and pouertie, thus ſpeaketh the lawgiuer in the chapter afore going: <hi>Likewiſe if a man ſell his daughter to be a ſeruant, ſhe ſhall not gee out as men ſeruants doe. If ſhe pleaſe not her maister, who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trethed her vnto himſelfe, then ſhall he cauſe to buy her, he ſhall haue no power to ſell her to a ſtrange people, ſeeing he deſpiſed or defloured her. But if he hath betrothed her vnto bys ſenne, he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6202:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6202:14"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:6202:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6202:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6202:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6202:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6202:17"/>ſhall deale with her according to the cuſtome of the daughters.</hi> So that ye ſee howe the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in this ſort ſold to be a ſeruant by her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, became by this ſale bound to the power of her maiſter, to bee at his appointing in the caſe of marrying, and ſuch was the condition of all other ſeruants by the law of God in this reſpect, and that the ſonnes alſo were not left vnto their owne direction, no although that they were otherwiſe free, beſides that this place doth prooue the ſame, directly affirming that the father of the free ſon might betroth him vnto his bond maid, it ſhall in his place ſufficientlie hence forward likewiſe appeare.<note place="margin">The ſeventh reaſon draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Honor thy father &amp; mother. &amp;c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides al this what clearer euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce can we haue on our ſide, then the fift commandemét, in the which childré are cómanded to honor their fathers and mothers, with a bleſſing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to thoſe which perform the ſame: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we gather by the nature of contraries, that there is a curſe alſo belonging vnto all thoſe children that ſhal diſhonor them. And in that God willeth that the parentes by their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould be honoured, he meaneth, that they ſhould in all humilitie and modeſtie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence them, with all dutifull ſubmiſsion, be obedient vnto them, and with all willingnes ſhew themſelues thankfull for their procrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, education, ſuſtentation, and all other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, that vnder God they haue receiued from them, being readie by all meanes they poſſible may, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, to imitate
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6202:17"/>and expreſſe towards them the nature of the Storke, whoſe propertie (as they write of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) is to prouide meat, and feed their dams, when through age they grow ſo olde, that they are not able for to help themſelues, that is to ſay, they muſt to their verie vtmoſt ſeeke to make them recompence and requitall of ſome part of thoſe vnrequitable paines the which their louing parentes haue taken with them, and make ſome a mends for the vnconteruaillable kindnes that they haue ſhewed towards them. But where they beſtowe themſelues in mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age without the conſent of their parentes, there they do fault and make a breach of dutie in all theſe three reſpectes, that is to ſay, they neither reuerence, obey, nor ſhew themſelues thankful vnto them. For, reuerence conſiſteth in this, that we carie towards them a certaine honeſt and modeſt ſhamefaſtnes, ioyned with abaſhfull awfulnes &amp; ſtanding in feare of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the which worketh in vs a conceiuing of ſuch an opinion and eſtimation of them, as that we haue an eſpeciall reſpect and regard of them in doing or not doing of things, neither of a care to pleaſe them, or of a feare to offend them. Obedience herein ſheweth foorth it ſelfe, in that willinglie without murmuring or grudging we be willing to be ordered, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, guided, and ruled by them, being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to do all lawfull thinges the which they command vs, &amp; to refraine from thoſe things the which they ſhall forbid vs. Thankfulneſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6202:18"/>beſides that, there are many other branches, is alwaies mindful of benefits receiued, and therefore carrieth continually a vigilant and watchfull eie towards the partie by whome it hath bene pleaſured, that no diſcurteſie in any caſe bee offered, or anie occaſion mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, whereby he may conceiue vnkindnes. And by this familiar deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe three heades, whereof ſtandeth chieflie the honor due vnto parentes, we may clearlie ſee, that thoſe which in wedding tarie not for the conſent of their fathers and mothers, do nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtand in any awfull feare of them, as who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would be lorn to offend or diſpleaſe, nor yet giue ouer themſelues in all thinges to be gouerned and aduiſed by them, or haue any regard that they be not cauſers to make their friendes or parents conceiue hardlie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindlie of them, when as it is more then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that in matters concerning their duety towardes their parentes, no greefe cutteth neerer vnto the heart then this, when they entangle themſelues contrarie vnto their minde and liking. And therefore ſuch chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as match in this ſort, as it were in ſpite of the teeth of their fathers and mothers are neither reuerent, obedient, nor thankfull vnto them, and ſo conſequentlie they doe not honour them, wherby they incurre and runne into the curſe of God, the which muſt without true and vnfeigned repentance pull downe vpon the heades of themſelues and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6202:18"/>their families the fearfull plagues of God. His heauie and hot indignation againſt them to their vtter ſubuerſion, decay and ruine,<note place="margin">The eight reaſon from the place of Paule. Colloſ. 3.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>S. Paule in his epiſtle vnto the colloſsians, willeth children to bee obedient vnto their parents in al things, &amp; giueth a reaſon therof ſaying, <hi>For that is well pleaſing vnto the Lord.</hi> Out of this place I reaſon after this maner, to prooue that the good wil of the parents muſt be ſought for &amp; obtained by the children in their contracts of mariage. Whatſoeuer plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God, the ſame ought of al children to be practiſed ſo far foorth as it concerneth their place &amp; calling: but to marie with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of parents is a thing that pleaſeth God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore children in their mariages ought to haue the conſent &amp; allowance of their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. That euerie one in his calling ought to labor to do that thing which pleaſeth God, I take to be a caſe ſo cleare, that no man doubteth of the ſame ſo that to go about to prooue this were as needles a thing, as to labor to prooue that water is moiſt, fire is hot, or that it is day at high noone. If any thing in the former reaſon be denied, it wil be this, that to mary with the conſent of the parents pleaſeth not God, the which although it be as euident &amp; apparent as the former, and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be denied of any that hath a forehead at al (for who, except he cary a face of braſſe, can be doubtfull of this, that God is well pleaſed with the matching of children by the conſent of their parents, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided alwaies that the mariage be in his feare
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6202:19"/>the which caution is to be obſerued through out this whole controuerſie, either handled alreadie or to be touched herafter) yet for the ſake of the ſimpler ſort, the which of ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for the moſt part offend in this kinde of priuie contractes, I will make this point plaine alſo after this maner. All obedience vnto parents is wel pleaſing to the Lord, but for the ſons to take wiues, &amp; the daughters to take husbands with the liking and approouing of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers, is an eſpeciall obedience vnto them, and ſuch as all parentes wiſh euen with all their heart to haue in al their children performed towards them, therefore to marie with the conſent of parents is ſuch an action wherewith God is well pleaſed. The verie wordes of Paule, where he ſaieth, <hi>Children o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey your parentes in all things,</hi> doe ſufficientlie warrant, that all obedience vnto parentes is wel pleaſing vnto God, and the ſame is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe auouched by Paule before in the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle vnto the Epheſians, where ſpeaking of the dutie of children, he hath theſe words, <hi>Children obey your parents in the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.1.</note> ſetting downe this reaſon, <hi>for it is right.</hi> And that fathers and mothers do hold themſelues o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beied, when their children be ruled and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by them in the choiſe of their wiues and husbands, is ſo euident, that no man can gainſay it. It muſt therefore needes follow, that God is well pleaſed, when they do get them yoakefellowes with the conſent of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6202:19"/>their parents. Nay, as it is trueth not to bee doubted of, that God his fauour and alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance goeth alwaies with thoſe eſpouſals, or betrothings the which are ratified and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed with the aſſent of thoſe that bare vs, and vnto whom we doe owe our being, becauſe that herein we do perform a chiefe point of obedience, the which God looketh for, and requireth at our hands: ſo on the contrarie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal ioin our ſelues in the band of matrimony, &amp; make no reckoning of the authoritie of our ſuperiours, ſtepping in betweene, God cannot behold thoſe bridals with a cheerefull and a ſmyling countenance but is diſpleaſed, and frowneth at the ſame, becauſe that we haue forgotten ourſelues in a principall part of our child-like and dutiful obedience. For if we muſt ſubmit our ſelues, and lay downe our handes vnder the feet of our parentes in all things, yeelding our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in the verie ſmalleſt cauſes, becauſe God hath ſo commanded, as the Apoſtle ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſo many wordes doth clearly teach vs, then doubtles much more in the caſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying (a matter of ſuch force &amp; importance, as whereupon for the moſt part dependeth our making or marring) we ought willinglie to put our necks vnder the wholſome yoake of their fatherlie power, vpon whoſe conſent or refuſall lieth the eſtabliſhing or diſanul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our handfaſting our ſelues without their agreement thereunto.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6202:20"/>
            <p> But it will here be replied,<note place="margin">The ninth reaſon, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the anſwering of an obiection concerning the reſtraint of childrens obedience.</note> that Paule him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a kind of ſhew of ſome contrarietie, reſtreineth the general obedience of children commanded in the third to the Colloſsians to to bee perfourmed vnto their parentes in all thinges and draweth the ſame into a more ſtraight and narrowe compaſſe in his Epiſtle vnto the Epheſians, where he will haue their dutie to bee no further yeelded vnto them then in the Lord, and therefore vnleſſe it may plainlie be prooued, that to haue the conſent of parentes in mariage is a thing commanded by the word of God, children are freed &amp; ſet at libertie from giuing obedience thereunto. I anſwere, that the one place is a good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and expoſition vnto the other, ſo that this precept: <hi>Children obey your parentes in all things,</hi> ought worthelie to bee expounded by that other: <hi>Children obey your parente; in the Lord:</hi> that is (as I expound it, letting goe all other interpretations) in all ſuch thinges as are not againſt the Lorde, or which in the Scriptures are commaunded by the Lord. Which interpretation I doe the rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, becauſe I ſee it to bee warranted by the anſwere the which Peter &amp; Iohn in the Acts doe make vnto the chiefe rulers of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, whereby they excuſe themſelues for not obeying their inhibition forbidding them to preach any more in the name of Ieſus, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to obey you rather them God iudge ye.</hi> Whereby
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6202:20"/>we are taught, that not onelie in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of our parentes, but alſo of all other our ſuperiours be they Kinges, rulers or Magiſtrates of any other condition whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, all which are comprehended vnder the name of parentes, that if they inioine vs to do any thing a gainſt that obedience the which we owe vnto God, we are not indeed viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to reſiſt, but we muſt with patience abide ſuch puniſhment as they ſhall lay vpon vs, rather then in obeying them we ſhould diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God, vnto whom of good right wee are bound aboue and before al others be they of neuer ſo high and excellent places. For there is a double obedience, that is, a certaine firſt, chief, &amp; moſt ſoueraign obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the which is proper and belongeth vnto God, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundarie or inferiour obedience the which is due and appertaining vnto men.<note place="margin">A moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraral rule the which ad mitteth no exception.</note> So that in all our actions what ſoeuer belongeth vnto this life this is a moſt generall rule the which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth or receiueth none exception: <hi>God must be obeied before, or rather then men.</hi> To returne therefore vnto the matter in hand, the obedience of children to their parentes muſt (I grant) be limitted and bounded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the railes and liſtes of our obedience pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culier vnto God, that is to ſay, Childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are no further to obey the commandements of their parentes, then ſo far foorth as the ſame be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable and agreable vnto the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God. But this neuer a whit relieueth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6202:21"/>their bad and vnfollowable courſe the which in marriage will be their owne caruers, and make their owne choiſe without the conſent and allowing of their parents, the which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that hath hither to bene alleaged, we wil yet further more largelie and more expreſlie prooue out of the word of God, and confirme, that ſo it ought to be.</p>
            <p>And now are we come indeed vnto a more higher, and neerer point, and the which will ſeeme ſtranger both vnto a great ſort of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and alſo ſerue verie ſtronglie to curbe the vnbrideled &amp; ſtay-les affections of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of inconſiderate and vnaduiſed youthes (if by the warrant of the word of God they may be ſtayd) when as it ſhall bee plainlie laid downe vnto them, that not only they are in their handfaſtinges &amp; making ſure in mariage to haue the conſent of their fathers and mothers, and that, not ſeeking for the ſame, they breake Gods commandement, but alſo when it ſhall be ſhewed, that choiſe of wiues and husbands for them, is not in their power, but in the authoritie of their fathers, and that this, both in plaine wordes is ſet downe in the ſcriptures, and may moreouer be prooued by many examples as a generall vſe and cuſtome to haue bene obſerued not onely of the godlier ſort among the Iewes, but alſo among the gentiles, which had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther direction but the law of nature: When I ſay, it ſhall be euidentlie prooued, that the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6202:21"/>choiſe in mariage, of husbands and wiues for their ſonnes and daughters, was in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and not in the children, I thinke there will no queſtion at all afterwards bee made, whether the conſent of the parents be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to be had or no in the mariage of their children, foraſmuch as if it be not in the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to make their owne choiſe, much leſſe may they marie without their parents liking:<note place="margin">Children in mariage may not make their owne choiſe, therefore much leſſe ought they marie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their friends con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</note> for thoſe that of themſelues may not doe the leſſer, cannot be ſaid to bee at their owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betie to doe the greater: but children in mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of mariage may not do the leſſer, that is, make their owne choiſe, which is a leſſe thing then to marie without conſent, therefore it muſt of neceſsitie follow, that in marying they muſt haue the conſent of their parentes.</p>
            <p>That children may not make their owne choiſe in marying, I prooue after this maner: No childe may take vpon him the duetie and office of his father: To make choiſe of hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes and wiues for ſonnes &amp; daughters in mariage, is the duetie and office of fathers: therefore children in mariage may not make their owne choiſe, and ſo conſequently may not marie without the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of their fathers. The firſt, that children may not take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the office of their fathers, I take as graunted. The ſecond, that parents ought to take wiues vnto their ſonnes, and husbandes vnto their daughters, I will prooue by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God in ſundrie places, and by mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6202:22"/>reaſon drawen from thoſe places. And in this point, If I beſtow the more labour, I ſhall the rather be borne withall, becauſe it is the moſt waightie part of al this diſcourſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, if I ſhal happely, or rather vnhappilie, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie be deemed tedious or ouerlong, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitableneſſe of the matter, if God giue grace, that being of ignorance in the moſt negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted before, it may now vpon knowledge be put in diligent practiſe hereafter, ſhall eaſily (I truſt) procure my pardon. And my good hope and earneſt prayer alſo is, that this my trauaile ſhall not be in vaine, but that al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie fathers and mothers ſeeing clearly at the length what charge by God himſelfe is laide vpon them, will be carefull in time to make meete choiſe for their children, &amp; that all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull and obedient ſonnes and daughters vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that it is no deuiſe of man, but the expreſſe commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God that their fathers &amp; mothers ſhould prouide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wiues &amp; husbands, wil ceaſe henceforth to take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them the office of their parentes, and with all willingnes, be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſtand in theſe caſes to the choice of their elders, which they ſhall make for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the feare of the Lord, &amp; agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably vnto his word, or at leaſt wiſe in no caſe aſſure themſelues, vnleſſe themſelues be ſure of their conſent.</p>
            <p>Now let vs ſee the places of Scripture, by which it may appeare that the choiſe of hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands for the daughters, and of wiues for the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6202:22"/>ſonnes is by the commandement of God himſelfe laid vpon the parentes,<note place="margin">Places of ſcripture proouing that pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ought to prouide wiues &amp; huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds for their ſonnes and daughters. Deut. 7.3.</note> concerning which matter, in the booke of Deuteronomy we read thus. <hi>Neither ſhatt thou make marta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> (he ſpeaketh of the ſeuen nations, the which by the Iewes were vtterly to bee rooted out) <hi>neither giuethy daughter vnto his ſon, nor take his daughter vnto thy ſonne.</hi> Here God giueth an eſpecial charge vnto al fathers among the Iewiſh natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that at no hand they ſhould place in mariage, citheir their ſonnes with the daughters of thoſe nations, or take of their ſons to be husbands for their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the which precept had bin in vain, if they had not had this power and authoritie ouer their children, or if their ſons and daughters had bene at their own libertie in theſe caſes to haue made their owne choiſe, for they might eaſilie haue replied, that their children in theſe pointes were not to be at their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and the children might haue complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the hard dealing of their fathers in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their right in making their owne matches, if any ſuch priuiledge had belonged vnto them: but the fathers neither taking any exception againſt God, to excuſe themſelues from this dutie, nor the ſonnes pleading that by this lawe their intereſt ſhoulde be impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, doth argue ſufficientlie that it was the ordinarie courſe of that time for parentes to giue their children in mariage, and that their children were wel content with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6202:23"/>doings in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>It will here peraduenture be ſaide, That God by making this law, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> ſetteth not downe an order the which he would haue generally to be obſerued of the parentes in all matches of their children, yea euen with their owne people and nation, but onelie directeth them what they ſhould doe concerning mariage of their ſonnes and daughters among thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen accurſed nations, &amp; this alſo to preuent a miſchiefe, leaſt that by making and ioyning any ſuch affinitie, they might be pulled and drawen away from the true worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God vnto idolatrie and ſuperſtition. I anſwere, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
               </label> that God, when he gaue vnto them this commandement, had indeed an eſpeciall regard to meet with before hand this danger of hauing his people caried by ſuch matches to run a whoring after ſtrange Goddes, but this notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding prooueth not, that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers libertie to place his children in wedlock was not general amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people of his own nation, but that hee had this authoritie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them onelie from marying with that wicked people for feare of ſpirituall infection and pollution: for that they had this power ouer their children in prouiding the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage euen within their own land, and limits of their owne countrie, it is moſt clearlie to be ſeene in the laſt chapiter of the booke of Iudges, where the Iſraelites hauing geuen that great and fearfull ouerthrowe vnto their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6202:23"/>brethren the Beniamites, for their maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of that moſt horrible outrage in defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in verie ſhamefull and beaſtlie maner of the Leuites concubine, bound themſelues by a ſolemne oth, and ſware, ſaying: <hi>None of vs ſhal giue his daghter vnto the Bentamits to wife.</hi> This oath for my part (reſeruing to others their contrarie iudgment) I doe not in anie caſe allowe, but condemne the ſame as raſh, and vnaduiſed, the which trulie repenting themſelues of their raſhnes, they might with farre better conſcience haue broken then kept, and I could alleadge many reaſons to confirme mine opinion, but that is not apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to this preſent argument, neither yet any part of my purpoſe in this place, nor at this time, onely I bring it to ſhew, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is manifeſt that they made no doubt of their libertie in diſpoſing of their children in mariage, nor of their readines to obey them in that behalfe, for if they might not ouerrule them in this matter, or their children had bin to make their owne choiſe, they had bene worthy of double blame, both in taking vpon them the placing of their daughters, and alſo in binding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with an oth for the due execution and performance of that thing,<note place="margin">The raſhneſſ of the Iſrali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taketh not a way their ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in making choiſe for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in their ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ages.</note> the which they had no right to lay vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them.</p>
            <p>And howſoeuer it be that this place may be thought of ſome, not of force ſuffiicient to warrant this authoritie of Parentes, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the choiſe for their ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6202:24"/>in their marriages, becauſe the oath was taken vnaduiſedlie (albeit that their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in one thing, be not plea good inough to disfrauchize them of their freedome and libertie in an other thing) yet if the cauſe had bene good, it ſhall appeare by an other place, that they might by oath haue bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for the not giuing of their daughters in mariage, whereby may bee gathered that the choiſe in theſe caſes lay in the parentes, and not in their children: for herein they fault in this action, not that they ſeeke to keepe their right and authoritie in prouiding for their children, but in that they make an oath both raſh, and full of crueltie againſt their brethren.</p>
            <p>Now that the choiſe was in parents of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding wiues &amp; husbands for their children and in ſuch ſort, that they might in honeſt &amp; godlie matches bind themſelues ſo to do, it is certaine by that which we reade in the laſt chapiter of the booke of Nehemiah, who cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed manie of them that were returned from the captiuitie, not onely to take an oath that they would not take wiues vnto their ſonnes nor husbands vnto their daughters of the ſtrange nations there ſpecified, but alſo made them to curſe and ban themſelues, and to wiſh heauie iudgmentes and plagues of God to fall vpon them, if they ſhould doe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie.</p>
            <p>That the mater may be out of all doubt &amp;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6202:24"/>controuerſie, it ſhall not grieue me to ſette downe the wordes as they lie in the text:<note place="margin">Nehem. 13.23.24.</note> 
               <hi>In thoſe daies alſo</hi> (ſaieth Nehemiah) <hi>I ſaw Iewes that maried wiues of Aſhdod, of Ammon, and of Moah. And their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpake halfe in the ſpeech of Aſhdod, and could not ſpeake in the Iewes lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and according to the language of the one people, and of the other people. Then I reprooued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and curſed them, and ſmote certaine of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; pulled of their hair, and took an oth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God: ye ſhall not giue your daughters vnto their ſonnes, neither ſhall you take of their daughters vnto your ſonnes, nor for your ſelues.</hi> Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall with him ſelfe weigh and conſider of this moſt excellent and worthy man, of his true godlineſſe and zeale in religion, of his great care &amp; forwardnes to build vp the citie and Temple, of his faithfulnes in his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and rule ouer the people committed to his charge, he may not go about to offer vnto him this iniurie, inſomuch as once dreaming that a man of his holines, religion, zeale, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and godlineſſe would ſo much as make the very leaſt motion of any vnlawful matter to his people, much leſſe enforce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by oath to enter into ſuch a courſe, whereby they might eaſilie haue bin periured had they not in this caſe well knowen their fatherlie pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ouer their children, and bene perſwaded of their tractable readines in this matter to bee ruled by them. Such was the diſcipline of that time, and in ſuch awe ſtood dutifull children
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6202:25"/>vnto their louing fathers in thoſe daies, that being therennto required by the magiſtrate, they durſt not onely pawne their credit, but that which more is, giue their oath, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard their conſcience, vpon the aſſured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence wheich they repoſed in their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens willingnes to betake &amp; betroth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto ſuch yoke fellowes as they ſhould appoint and make choiſe of for them in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt matrimonie to lead their liues withall. Yet doe I not thinke the contrarie, but that in thoſe ages, like as in our time there were many both ſonnes and daughters, which are like vnrulie coltes and vntamed heifars could not be brought vnto this paſſe, nor yet be yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked within this bow, but the ſturdie froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſome certaine, is no diſproofe of the dutifull obedience of the better ſort, neither was there anie more required of the fathers, then that according vnto God his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, ſo far as in them lay, they ſhould doe their partes to keep their children within this compaſſe: that is to ſay, they were to prouide matches for them within their owne people, to charge them in regard of that honour, the which by God his commandement they did owe vnto them, that they yeelded vnto their fathers choiſe, and hauing gone thus far, they haue ſufficientlie done that which vnto them belonged, and for the reſt, they were to leaue their rule leſſe children vnto the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God, and correction of the magiſtrate, who
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6202:25"/>in caſes of diſobedience, where the authority of parents could beare no ſway,<note place="margin">Deut 21, 18.</note> was by God himſelfe appointed to miniſter correction ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto the qualitie of the tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>To make an end of this ninth reaſon, in the which I may be thought to haue dwelled too long,<note place="margin">Almoſt ſtrong place our of Ieremie to proue that that the choiſ was in parents to prouide ſit matches for their children in mariage.</note> I will ſhut vp this place with an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie taken out of the prophet Ieremie, &amp; with the iudgment of M. Caluin (a moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie inſtrument of Chriſt his Church in our time) vpon the ſame, the which ſhall ſtrike this matter ſtone dead (as they ſay) and ſo goe on to other proofes, and theſe ſhall ſerue as a ſtrong naile to faſten all the reſt together, &amp; to make ſure all the other teſtimonies of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in this foreſaid ninth reaſon, already quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the faithfull alleadging of the which places, vnto ſuch end and purpoſe, and by the holie Ghoſt they are directed, beſides that, I haue the teſtimonie of a cleare conſcience to beare witneſſe of my fearfull carefulneſſe to deale ſincerelie and faithfullie in the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the word of God, If I ſhall be therunto at any time hereafter vrged, I can bring alſo the confirmation of the beſt and moſt learned writers.</p>
            <p>Ieremie in the 29 chapiter of his propheſie among other reaſons the which hee vſeth to comfort the people in their long &amp; hard cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie,<note place="margin">Ievem. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6.</note> and to put them in hope that they ſhall aſſuredlie return, at the length ſpeaketh
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6202:26"/>vnto them by the commandement of God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner: <hi>Take you wiues, &amp; beget ſons &amp; daughters, and take wiues for your ſonnes, and giue your daughtes to husbands, that they may beare ſonnes and daughters, that you may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed there and not be diminsſhed.</hi> Vpon this place Caluin writeth after this maner. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (ſaieth he) the prophet willeth them to <hi>take wiues for their ſons, and to giue their daughters to be maried,</hi> this is according to the lawfull order and courſe of nature, becauſe that this were too prepoſterous, or ouerthwart and topſituruy dealing, that yoong men and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, ſhould get them either husbandes or wiues at their owne luſt and pleaſure. God therefore in this place ſpeaketh according vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the common rule, when as hee comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth yoong men to be linked in matrimonie no otherwiſe, but by the commandement of their parentes: and maidens alſo not to marie any husbands, but ſuch as to whom they ſhal be giuen. Here you may ſee in few words confirmed that,<note place="margin">Four eſpeciall poyntes to be noted out of the wordes of Calum.</note> which in ſo manie I haue at large ſet downe before: where firſt it is to bee noted, that childrens marying according to the choiſe of their parentes, is a thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God. Secondlie, that it is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto the law of nature. Thirdlie, that it was a generall rule and common practiſe. Fourthly, that the contrarie dealing is prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous and ouerthwart, and as far out of ſquare and order, as if the cart ſhould bee
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6202:26"/>placed and ſet before the horſe. And marke further, that in all theſe places cited in this ninth reaſon, God ſaith not,<note place="margin">It is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, &amp; not a permiſsion, that parentes in mariage ſhould make choiſe for their chils dreſt.</note> that parentes if they wil, may prouide wiues for their ſonnes, and husbandes for their daughters: That it were meete and requiſite that it ſhould be ſo, but vſeth euerie where the imperatiue mood, that is, commandeth that it be ſo, and leaueth it not at randome to our diſcretion to chooſe whether we will haue it to bee ſo, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to that end that we ſhould knowe, that if wee that are parentes ſhall neglect our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in this behalfe, wee ſhall not paſſe away with the matter ſlightlie and lightlie, as if it were a leſt &amp; a trifle, but that we ſhall anſwer for it, as for a tranſgreſsion and breach of his commandement.</p>
            <p>Hauing therefore giuen this breefe caueat and warning blow vnto fathers and mothers to think hereafter more aduiſedlie vpon their duties in beſtowing of their children, I take my leaue and farewell of this reaſon, giuing al yoong men and maidens in like maner to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that if they ſhal henceforth refuſe to be ordered and directed by their parentes, they ſhall be found rebels againſt God, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors againſt the law of nature, breakers of the common rule and cuſtome of all well gouerned children, and ſuch, ſo far as in them is, would bring in al confuſion and diſorder, in altering and changing Gods owne courſe, to ſet vp and eſtabliſh their owne vnbride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6202:27"/>luſt and lawles affection.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we haue ſeen how farreforth the Scriptures, and places of the old Teſtament, doe ſtand firmely on our ſide, for the proofe of this queſtion, the which we haue taken v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, namely t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at mariages are not to bee made without the conſent of parents, the which as we perſwade our ſelues, wee haue proued with the a du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>intage, ſhe wing that not onely children, in mariage ought to haue the good wil &amp; leaue of their fathers &amp; mothers, butalſo, if we ſnal look more neerlie into the cauſe, that the choiſe in mariage belong vnto them Now in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he tenth place I wil make this plaine alſo, by one cleare teſtimony and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes out of the newe Teſtament, the which I take from out of the ſeauenth Chapiter of the firſt Epiſtle of S. Paul vnto the Corinthians, whoſe wordes be theſe:<note place="margin">The tenth reaſon out of the words of Paule. 1. Cor. 7.36.37.38.</note> 
               <hi>But if any man thinke that it is vncomly for his vingin, if ſhee paſſe the flowre of her age, and neede ſo require, let him doe what he will, reſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth not, let them be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried. Neuertheles he that ſtandeth firme in his heart, that he hath no neede, but hath power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his owne will, and hath ſo decreede in his heart, that he wil keepe his virgin, he doeth well. So then he that grueth her to martage, doth wel, but he that giueth her not to mariage doth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> The purpoſe of Paul in this place is to giue counſel vnto patentes, what courſe they were beſt to take for their children con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their beſtowing of them in mariage,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6202:27"/>or letting them remaine ſingle, according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the aſſured and certaine knowledge that they haue of their abilitie to liue chaſt, or their neede, otherwiſe to vſe that lawfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie, the which God hath ordained againſt fornication, which is to marie, ſo that thoſe which haue the gift of chaſtitie, hee would not haue conſtrained to ioine themſelues in wedlocke, nor thoſe which are not able to be forced to liue ſingle. This is brieflie the ſumme of the place. Concerning thoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that cannot liue ſingle, hee willeth their parentes to looke vnto them betimes, leaſt that their too long differring and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying the matter breed ſome inconuenience. And this is it that hee ſaieth: <hi>If ante man thinke that it is vncomely for his virgine, if ſhee paſſe the flower of her age, and neede ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, let him doe what he will, he ſinneth not: Let them marie.</hi> Which laſt clauſe plainely teacheth, that looke what is ſaide of the daughter, is to be vnderſtood alſo of the ſon: for one cannot be maried alone. Speaking therefore in the plurall number, he meaneth as well the ſonnes as the daughters, touching whom this is his counſaile: That parente<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when their children come once to ſuch yeares, that they are readie to marie,<note place="margin">The ſumme o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his counſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto paren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in time to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide fit ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> children.</note> ſhould in due time haue conſideration hereof, not giuing occaſion, by cauſing them ſtay too long, either to bee derided, or laughed to ſcorne as ſtale bachelers, or otherwiſe to bee
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6202:28"/>ſuſpected of bad husbandrie, or huſwifrie, or of pride and diſdaining all others, being ſo nice &amp; coy, that they think none fine enough to match withal, or that there is in them ſome ſecrete &amp; hidden vice or infirmitie the which maketh them vnfit for mariage, or otherwiſe of couetouſneſſe, becauſe they are loth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part with mony towards their maintenance, protracting &amp; delaying the time longer then the nature and diſpoſition of their ſonnes &amp; daughters will beare, ſo that by their means being thus deferred and put off, when as they are not able any longer to forbeare, their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents neglecting to prouide that remedie for them the which Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath ordained, they burne in luſt and commit follie. Their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers therefore perceiuing that ſo it ought to be, that is, their children with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare of ſome inconuemence cannot tary any longer vnmatied, ought worthelie to haue this wiſe care for them, in time to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them of fit and honeſt matches. This then is the driſt of this place, that parentes ſhould by all gentle and faire meanes true out and ſearch the ſtate and diſpoſition of their children towards mariage when by reaſon of conuenient age they are fit for the ſome, and by conference and queſtioning with them, get from them howe they ſtand affected this way, and accordinglie as they ſhall haue ſure notice how they are giuen, to ſuffer them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to remaine ſingle, or els that they (as it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6202:28"/>is their fatherlie dutie) doe prouide for them godlie wiues and husbandes.<note place="margin">The inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience that groweth by this that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents followe not Paule his counſaile in prouiding fit matches for their children</note> Thus we ſee how pregnant and plentifull a text this is to teach that it lieth in the parents to make due choiſe for their children in the caſe of matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: And becauſe that ſmall regard is had hereof in many now adaies, he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it commeth that ſome children giue themſelues ouer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the luſtes of the fleſh, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; filthy fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: others, contrary vnto the lawes both of God and nature, breake in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the duties of their fathers, and vnnatural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and not child-like, without the priuitie &amp; conſent of their parentes make their owne matches &amp; the ſame for the moſt part ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward, that they bring the gray haires of their parentes vnto their griefe and ſorrowe to the graue, and themſelues beſides waſtfully ſpending all that they haue, liue all their life long in continuall and dailie home braules, and houſhold ſtrifes and diſcordes.</p>
            <p>You therefore that be fathers and mothers I moſt earneſtlie and hartilie exhort and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you for the loue of God and in the tender bowels and mercie of Ieſus Chriſt our moſt gratious redeemer,<note place="margin">An exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto al pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note> that you will at the length awake, and rouſe vp your ſelues out of this deadlie ſleepe of careleſneſſe, wherewith you haue bene long oppreſſed, making litle or none accountes at all of this waightie and neceſsarie dutie of prouiding vertuous wiues and husbandes for your
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6202:29"/>ſonnes and daughters, delay the time hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth no longer, put in diligent vre and practiſe this wholſome counſaile of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, lay off all rigorous auſterenes and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and in the ſpirite of lenitie and milde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, queſtion and confer, talke and reaſon with your ſonnes and daughters, when they be come vnto ripe veares, that you may learn how they are inclined concerning mariage, or ſole life: and if it bee ſo that you thinke, that through baſhfulneſſe and ſhamefaſtneſſe they will not dare to deale plainlie with you, nor freelie to vnfolde their mindes vnto you as they would doe vnto ſome of their famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, let it not grieue you to vſe this wiſe policie to fiſh out their purpoſe by ſome of their friendes vnto whome being great with them, they will not bee affraide to vtter the verie bottome of their heartes and inmoſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretes. And when you ſhall haue found, that it is ſafeſt for your honor, and meeteſt for their preſent eſtate, that you prouide for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to marie, goe about the ſame in the feare of God accordinglie, with faithfull and earneſt praier vnto God,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.12.</note> after the example of the godly Steward of Abraham in the book of Ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſis, that he wil both direct you in a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and chriſtian choiſe, and alſo incline and mooue the heartes of your children with all dutifull readines to ſtand vnto the ſame, And taking the matter in hand after this reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; chriſtian order, aſſure your ſelues that you
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6202:29"/>haue performed a good work, &amp; ſin not, for ſo Paule telleth you in plaine wordes, where he ſaith, <hi>Let him doe what he will, he ſinneth not.</hi> and a litle after, <hi>He that giueth her to marie,</hi> (meaning when the father by good triall had found out that otherwiſe ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not liue chaſt) <hi>ſinneth not.</hi> For in ſpeaking after this manner, he hath (no doubt) reſpect vnto that courſe, the which the Lord himſelfe in his word hath ſet down, &amp; the which alſo hath of the godlie bene practiſed euen from the beginning, as by many examples anon ſhall be ſhewed. There is therefore no danger of doing amiſſe, and of ſinning, if that you behaue your ſelues after this ſort in prouiding husbandes for your daughters, and in beſtowing of your ſonnes in honeſt wedlock. But rather on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part you ſhal verie greatly tranſgreſſe and offend, if ye ſhall neglect and forſlowe your dutie in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>And to all you that will bee counted godlie and dutifull children,<note place="margin">An earneſt ſute vnto all godly childs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> let mee in all humble and louing manner make this ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſuite and waightie motion, that you likewiſe hereafter will with all reuerence and aduiſedneſſe conſider, what dutie you owe vnto God, whoſe order this is, that you ſhold be ruled by your parents in all thinges, vnto whom he hath giuen ſuch high &amp; ſoueraigne power and authoritie ouer you, that he will haue euen thoſe ſolemn vowes and promiſes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6202:30"/>that you haue made vnto himſelfe to ſtoup and giue place vnto their conſent and alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſtriue no longer againſt God,<note place="margin">Num. 30.</note> but in all willingneſſe of minde put your neckes vnder his yoke: enter not violentlie into your fathers right: giue vnto them this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to thinke that they by their wiſe donie can, and for the louing care the which they beare towardes you, will prouide better for you, then you can doe for your ſelues: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that you are called after Chriſt by the glorious name of Chriſtians, who was obedient vnto his father euen vnto the death of the croſſe, let it therefore be no griefe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you to ſubmit your ſelues vnto them in that ſame thing, whereof you haue in the ſcriptures ſo manie notable and honourable preſidentes: if they ſhall be thought ſlacke in prouiding for them in due time, labour by all modeſt meanes that by ſome friendes they be put in mind of their duetie: ſince God hath commanded them to make choiſe for you, beſtow not your ſelues without their conſent but humble your ſelues by deuout and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full praiers before the throne of the almighty, that he in mercie will vouchſafe that your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall parentes vnto whoſe power you are ſubiect, ſetting aſide all carnall and earthly reſpectes, may in their choiſe for you haue his feare before their cies, and that your ſelues may not bee caried away after your owne fancies, but by the working of his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6202:30"/>holie ſpirite bee inwardlie and throughlie mooued with a godlie, chriſtian, and pure loue to imbrace thoſe which they ſhall haue choſen and prouided for you, as the godlie children in former ages haue done before you.</p>
            <p>And here I will alleadge,<note place="margin">The eleuenth reaſon from the common vſe &amp; practiſe of the godlie in former times.</note> for an other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the generall vſe and practiſe of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Fathers, Patriarches and other holie men in prouiding of wiues for their ſonnes, and husbandes for their daughters, together with the willing obedience of their children to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and take them ſo prouided, at their handes, to ſerue to prooue that it was a common lawe among thoſe that liued in thoſe times: for the ſonnes and daughters in matrimonicall caſes to be ordered and ruled by their fathers and mothers. For the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers doe holde, that generall vſe and cuſtome doe make a law. And what reaſon then is there to the contrary, but that this, the which hath ſo generallie and continuallie bene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, ſhould in like maner goe and be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a law, the which it may bee thought that God euen hereby woulde induce and leade men vnto, in that, when hee firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all things, and man laſt of all, ouer whom by the priuiledges of creation, he might wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie claime the right and power of a father, he doth not ſuffer him at his owne choiſe &amp; pleaſure to take vnto himſelfe the woman, made of his ſide, but brought her himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6202:31"/>him to be his wife, by which his fact (as I doe take it) was notablie prefigured or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadowed out vnto vs,<note place="margin">God as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a wife for Adam in Paradiſe.</note> that he would haue earthly fathers take that courſe in prouiding for their children in mariage, the which he being our heauenlie father tooke for his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſon Adam in paradiſe, that is, that they ſhould make choiſe of wiues and husbandes for their ſonnes and daughters, the which they ought as willinglie to receiue at the handes of their fathers, as Adam did his wife from the hand of God. If any of thoſe vnbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beled colts, the which think they may at their owne pleaſure make their own matches, ſhal for the defence and maintenance of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, dealing in this behalfe replie and ſay, that this example taken from the fact of God, doth no more warrant this courſe, the which ſo much diſliketh them,<note place="margin">A trifling ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill.</note> then it prooueth, that a father ought in like ſort to take a wife for his ſonne out of the rib of a man, and cloſe vp the place againe with fleſh, as God did in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam: I anſwere that this is a friuolous or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling cauill. For, as the making of Heuah of the rib of Adam, was inimitable, or vnfolow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, being a token of God his omnipotencie and almightie power: ſo the other, being ſuch as both without danger we may follow, and alſo (as hath bene plentifullie before ſhewed) wee are commaunded to followe, and now remaineth to make plaine, that the godlie from time to time did follow, might
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6202:31"/>verie well be a foretoken vnto vs, that God in the choiſe for our childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would haue that we ſhould do the like.</p>
            <p>And this ſeemeth yet further hereby to be confirmed,<note place="margin">God giueth Chriſt his ſon to be the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of his Church.</note> that when as our firſt parents through their diſobedience and breach of God his commandement had worthelie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferued to bee turned headlong out of the earthlie paradiſe, and had further through this their traſgeſsion, loſt ſo farre as in them lay the in heritance of the kingdome of heauen, both for themſelues and alſo for all their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, when as nowe there remained no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of recouering the ſame againe, but onelie by the meanes of a mariage to be made by faith betweene himſelfe and his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, the true and euer laſting ſonne of God: who knoweth not that this match before all times was concluded in the eternall and moſt wiſe counſaile of God the father, who gaue his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſonne Ieſus Chriſt in time to bee borne of the virgin Marie, that he ſhould not onlie be the ſpouſe and husband of his Church, the members of his bodie, of his fleſh, and of his bones,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh vnto the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, but alſo of his entire and tender loue vnto the ſame laid downe his life for it, that it being waſhed in his owne blood, wherwith it is all to be ſprinkled by the hand of faith, it may bee preſented as a pure virgin vnto his heauenlie father without ſpot or wrinkle.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6202:32"/>if therfore God the father made the choiſe of vs his church to be a wife for Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, who with vnſpeakable willingeſſe tooke the ſame at his hand, although ſinne greatlie blemiſhed and deformed, which ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes and deformities he couered notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by faith in his blood: Howe much more then ought earthlie fathers ſeeke out meet wiues &amp; husbands for their ſonnes and daughters, whoſe duties it is to accept &amp; like of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this ſort prouided &amp; choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </p>
            <p>But if any ſhal thinke theſe examples to be far fetcht (albeit they be vſed of men of great note in this ſe fe ſame verie argument) I will now come vnto other preſidents,<note place="margin">Peter Martyr in his comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries vpon the booke of Iudges.</note> ſo manie as I can call to my remembrance, as I read them ſet downe in the booke of the ſcriptures.</p>
            <p>Abraham being verie olde and ſtroken in yeares, intending to make choiſe of a wife for Iſaac his ſonne,<note place="margin">Abraham by his ſteward prou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deth a wife for Iſaac his ſonne.</note> who at this time was no child of himſelfe, but fortie yeares of age, without imparting his counſaile vnto him, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this chardge vnto the Stewardes of his houſe, of whom he taketh an oth for his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dealing in this buſineſſe, whereas, had it either bene the cuſtome of that time, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe law full for children in theſe caſes to haue choſen for themſelues at their owne will and pleaſure, it had bene moſt meete and conuenient that his father ſhould haue dealt with Iſaac his ſonne, &amp; not with his ſeruant concerning.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:6202:32"/>
            <p> The ſeruant, as it may appeare by his procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,<note place="margin">The Steward goeth vnto the father of Rebeccha.</note> being wel acquainted with the practiſe of thoſe daies, dealeth not at all with Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha in theſe affaires, but goeth directly vnto her father Bethuell, at whoſe handes he doth obtaine her for his maſters ſonne. Bethuel the father,<note place="margin">Bethuel ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the match for his daughter.</note> at the Steward his propounding his ſute in the name of his maſter, by and by (as one not doubtfull of the obedience of his daughter) concludeth and ſhutteth vp the match, yet like a kinde father not minding to force his childe thereunto againſt her will, calleth for her, &amp; aſketh what ſhe ſayth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, who like a moſt louing childe, doeth willingly conſent vnto her his match, and taketh her iourney to goe with the ſeruant. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac, after that Rebecca is brought home vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him,<note place="margin">Rebeccha ſtandeth to the choiſe o her father.</note> entreth not into the deſperate vaine of the vnruly youths of our dayes, the which are caried away with the violent ſtreame of their head-ſtrong affections, &amp; therfore they ſhame not to blunder out theſe or ſuch like moſt vnreuerent and vnbefitting ſpeaches: My father, ſhall my father prouide me my wyfe? is he to make my choiſe? I am to marie for my ſelfe, and not for my father, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wil be my owne chooſer: Like ſhe me, I ſeeke no further, diſlike father or mother, or all the world beſides, I weigh it not &amp;c. you ſhall heare no ſuch thing of Iſaac. Nay he may worthely be a mirror or looking glaſſe for all ſonnes to prie into, and to behold how farre
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6202:33"/>they come ſhort from his ſubmiſſe and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience in this behalfe,<note place="margin">Iſaac taketh Rebecca pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for him, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth her.</note> for the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whom he neuer ſaw before, neither yet heard of ſo far as we reade, when he once vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth that ſhee is appointed for him by the choiſe of his father, the next ſaith, hee receiued her,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.67.</note> and loued her, and was comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after the death of his mother.</p>
            <p>Iaacob being hardly menaced and threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his brother Eſau,<note place="margin">Iaacob. Gen. 23.29.</note> in ſo much that hee was cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailed by his mother to flie away, for the ſafegarde of his life, is directed by his old and blinde father Iſaac, to goe to the houſe of his brother Laban, and from thence to take vnto his ſelf a wife, who obeying the voice of his father, we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto his vncle Laba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his hand receiueth his two wifes Leah &amp; Rachel. Iudah one of the xii.<note place="margin">Iudah beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth his ſons in mariage. Gen. 38.</note> Patriarchs, beſtowed in mariage his two ſons Er and Onan, and after their death putteth Tamar their widdowe in good hope, that if ſhe wil tary vntil his thirde ſonne Shelah, by reaſon of years ſhould be fit in mariage to be ioind with her, that he ſhould be a match and husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for her, in which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, albeit his purpoſe were indede to mock her, in reſpect of his inward intent priuy onely vnto himſelfe, yet Tamar in ſuch ſort taking him, as that ſhe ſuppoſed his heart and tongue to iumpe together, teacheth vs, that ſhe was ſo far perſwaded of his fatherly authority to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund his ſon when he ſhould growe to age conuenient, to be ruled by him, that without
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6202:33"/>ſeeking any further aſſurance, ſhee remaineth widdow, making her full and ſure reckoning, that in the end ſhe ſhould inioy him, becauſe his father, in whoſe authority hee was, to bee diſpoſed, would in truth perform his promis.<note place="margin">Caleb diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of the mariage of his daughter Acſah.</note> Caleb giueth his daughter Acſah, to be a wife vnto Othniel or Othoniel, who wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>her by his valour and prowes, in taking by force of arms Kiriahtſepher,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 15.16.17.</note> hauing made a general procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that whoſoeuer could effect that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble peece of ſeruice, ſhould obtaine her for his portion, whereby may eaſely be gathered, in what ſubiection children then were vnto their parents, in as much as it being a thinge very vncertaine, who ſhould doe this warlike feat, yet whatſoeuer he were, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God ſhould enable thereunto, hee made no doubt of his daughters taking him to be her husband. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non burning in vnordinate luſt towardes Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar the ſiſter of his brother Abſalon,<note place="margin">Tamar doeth acknowledg it to bee the right of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to determine of her mari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> age.</note> when as he went about to defile her, being craftely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed into his handes, through the ſuttle counſaile of Ionadab his friend, requeſting him to abſtaine from offering vnto her that great reproche and villany,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 13.</note> ſhee willeth him to aske her of her father in marriage.<note place="margin">Dauid.</note> The marriage it ſelfe I condemne as vnlawfull and inceſtuous, yet her requeſt importeth thus much, that ſhee well knewe, that ſhee was not to determine of her owne mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, but that the right thereof belonged to her father. Sampſon,<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.</note> although he faulted
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6202:34"/>in falling in loue with a woman of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins,<note place="margin">Iudge. 14</note> yet the Scriptures mention, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired his parents to procure her for him to be his wife. Where I would haue it of all youths to be well noted, after what ſort he ſped, with this his match of his owne making. But what ſhall I neede to make any longer ſtay in bringing foorth examples of the godlye to prooue this cuſtome of fathers in prouidinge mariage for their children, when as we haue teſtimony of the practiſe of the ſame euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the wicked, and that out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alſo.<note place="margin">Wicked pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes haue prouided ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages for their children and they haue dutifully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of their choiſe.</note> For Hagar albeit that ſhee her ſelfe ſometimes had beene a ſtubborne and diſobedient ſeruant vnto her miſtres Sarah, yet when Iſhmael her ſonne was once grown to man his eſtate, ſhee prouideth and taketh a wife for him out of the land of Fgypt. And we do not read the contrarie,<note place="margin">Gen. 21. Gen 14</note> but that hee willingly doth take her at his mothers choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, albeit that otherwiſe he were a fierce and cruell man, whoſe handes was againſt euery man, and euery mans hand againſt him. She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem the ſonne of Hamor a Lord of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites,<note place="margin">Shechem. Gen. 34.</note> hauing defloured Dinah the daughter of Iaacob, deſireth his father to get her of Iaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob to be his wife, which prooueth that hee both thought, that ſhe was not to bee placed in mariage, but by the appointment and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of her father, and that alſo he would not marrie her but by conſent and procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his father Hamor. And it is more then
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6202:34"/>probable or likely, that this cuſtome of the parents chooſing, and the childrens ſtanding to their choiſe, was continued from that age, vpward vnto the latter times of the Poets, and Comedy and Tragedy writers, in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the Heathen and vngodly, wher houſhould diſcipline and gouernment, was not altogether ſhaken and decayed, in ſo much that the maid ſayth in Euripides, when ſhe was ſued vnto for mariage:<note place="margin">The maid in Euripides.</note> My father will haue care of my mariage, it is not in my part to determine theſe matters. And agreably herunto reporteth Xenophon of king Cyrus, that being ſolicited and motioned vnto a great and honorable mariage, he anſwereth,<note place="margin">K. Cyrus.</note> that were her perſonage neuer ſo honorable and her dowrie to the purſe neuer ſo profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he will not at any hand meddle in this matter, becauſe that it was a thing beyonde his reach, and belonged altogether vnto the power and arbitrement of his parents. And this is a matter ſo common and wel knowen, that the very boyes in the Grammar ſchoole, are well acquainted therewithall out of the Comedies of Terence, and Plautus, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt make this caſe moſt plaine, that it was an ordinarie courſe in their times, that the fathers made the matches for their ſons and daughters in the way of mariage.</p>
            <p>Hereunto agreeth all antiquity, together with the better ſort of writers in all kinde of faculties, Diuines, Schoole men, Ciuilians,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6202:35"/>Canoniſtes,<note place="margin">The twelf rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the conſent of all ages, and the better ſort of all kinde of writers.</note> Decrees, Counſailes, yea and ſome of the Popes themſelues, who haue gone ſo far in theſe matters, that they doe ſtrike with the fiery thunderbolt of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, <hi>ipſo fac<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to,</hi> or ſo ſoone as the dede is done (as they ſay) not onely all thoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren the which without the conſent of theyr parentes, make theſe ſecret contractes and priuie matches, but alſo all ſuch as any way with their countenance, counſaile, aſſiſtance, preſence, or any other meanes ſhall helpe, fauour, further or procure the ſame, yea ſome other of them (as the learned well knowe) do hold ſuch kind of bargaines for no mariages, but pronounce them adulteries, fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and whordomes. The Ciuilians ſtande ſo ſtoutelie, and luſtelye, to mainteine the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents authority &amp; liberty in theſe caſes, that this is ſet downe among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a ruled caſe, (as Peter martyr reporteth) that if a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man haue once married with an husbande by the conſent of her parentes, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes they fall at ſuch farre, that they bee diuorced, if ſhee bee by perſwaſion moued to bee reconciled vnto the ſame partie, and bee againe married vnto him, that this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage being made without the conſent and knowledge of her parentes, is altogether fruſtrate, and vnlawfull, nay if any children haue ſuch parentes, as be taken with Phrenſie or madnes, ſo that they cannot haue theyr conſent in marriage, they will haue them
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6202:35"/>in ſuch a caſe, to obtayn the conſent of their ouerſeeres and gouernours: ſo ſincerely and ſoundlie, and agreable vnto the worde of God, doe the ciuill conſtitutions deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of the parentes right, in the placing and beſtowing of their children in matrimonye and wedlocke.<note place="margin">The plain and cleare iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the beſt Diuines of our time, touching this matter.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that it yet may be further apparent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to al men, that I am not ſingular in mine own conceite, or wedded vnto any priuatiudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this argument, I will adde a few teſtimonies of the latter Diuines of our age, the which tell a round tale in this buſines, and goe not behinde the doore for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at all, but deliuer theyr verdicts frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and freely without all obſcurity or dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And this I will the rather doe, that all parents and children, which are not vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voyd of al feeling, hauing of ignoraunce hitherto forflowed their duties on both ſides in this reſpect, may he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceforth, being compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about with ſuch a cloude of irrefregable or vngainſaiable witneſſes, which are aboue all exception againſt, bee touched with a due &amp; chriſtian ſorowfulnes of conſcience, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of healthful repentance, ſo that they may think erneſtly vpon the amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this gret fault, the one carefully prouiding chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> matches for their children in due time, &amp; the other in al dutiful humility, framing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to accept of their choiſe, leaſt that being preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſuch a heauy weight of ſo many
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6202:36"/>graue authorities from the lawe of nature God, and nations, there bee left no coloure of excuſe vnto them in that moſt terrible and feareful day of reckoning, when the thoughts of our hartes ſhall either accuſe vs, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.16</note> when as the Lotde him ſelfe ſhall iudge of the ſecretes of men, according vnto the Goſpell by leſus Chriſt, ſo that it will be then in vaine for any to make the plea of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, when as beſides the teſtimonye of his owne conſcience, he ſhall be conuinced by ſuch a multitude of moſt forcible &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty euidence, which at the barre will ſtand and plead againſt him. But to the witneſſes of the new writers.<note place="margin">Caluyn 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Caluin vpon the 3 verſe of the 24. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of Geneſis, among other thinges hath theſe wordes: Now this enſample ought to ſtand vs in ſtead of a generall rule, that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not contract themſelues in mariage, but by the arbitrement and appointment of their parentes. And truely this doth the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of nature teach vs, that children in a matter of ſuch waight ought to reſt vpon the will and pleaſure of their parentes: by howe much the barbarouſneſſe of the Pope is the more to bee deteſted, which hath dared to breake in ſunder this holie band, wherefore the wanton malepertneſſe and ſaucineſſe of youth is to bee reſtrained, that they raſhly poſt not vnto mariage without the counſaile of their fathers,</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:6202:36"/>
            <p> And againe in another place ſpeaking of Hagars prouiding a wife for her ſonne Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maell: Whereas Hagar is ſaid (ſaith Caluin) to haue taken a wife for her ſonne,<note place="margin">Gen. 21. verſe. 27.</note> this apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth vnto politike or ciuill gouernment. For when as mariage is an eſpeciall part of the life of man, it is meete that in making of the ſame, children ſhould be ruled by their parentes, and followe their aduiſe in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. This order, the which nature preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth and teacheth, we ſee to haue bene kept of Iſhmaell a wild man in the barbarouſneſſe of the wilderneſſe, that in the marieng of a wife he was obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto his mother. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we doe perceiue how cruell a monſter the Pope hath bene, in that he hath aduen tured to breake this holy lawe of nature. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more his ſhameleſneſſe was added hereunto, in that he hath vaunted that he giueth a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge vnto the vngodlie contempt of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, for the honour of holie wedlocke.</p>
            <p>Muſculus vpon the ſame place writeth thus: Behold the honeſtie of thoſe times. In our daies there is no need for parents to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide their ſonnes of wiues,<note place="margin">Muſculus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſtolen mariages.</note> when as youthes is ſuffered by a moſt bad cuſtome, to take vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelues wiues without the priuitie of their parentes, and ſuch mariages are confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Popes conſiſtories, as they tearme them. And a litle afterward: They that marie without the knowledge of their fathers and mothers, doe ſinne
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6202:37"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Againſt the firſt ordinance of mariage.<note place="margin">Let al youths diligently marke theſe thinges.</note> Loke before Cap. 2. Gen. vpon theſe wordes, <hi>And hee brought her vnto Adam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 Againſt the commandement of God: Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thy father and thy mother.</item>
                  <item>3 Againſt the law of nature, which is this: Do not vnto another that thing, the which thou wouldeſt not haue to be done vnto thy ſelfe.</item>
                  <item>4 Againſt publike honeſty, &amp; good manners.</item>
                  <item>5 Againſt the ciu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll laws, the which do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne priuy and ſtolen mariages.</item>
                  <item>6 Againſt the holynes of wedlocke, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings wherof are by this meanes defiled.</item>
                  <item>7 Againſt the examples of our elders. Here in this Chapiter. Afterwards chap. 28. <hi>And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit Iacob loued Rachel, yet did hee not priuilye ſteal her away, but ſerued for her at the pleaſure of her father, vntill that he might receue her at his handes being lawfully deliuered.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 Againſt youth it ſelf, the which through this raſhnes doth very gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly hinder &amp; hurt it ſelf That priuy &amp; ſtolen mariages are void and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> none effect, if the father giue not his conſent.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>EXod 22. <hi>Although a maiden be intiſed yet ſhall ſhe not be maried vnto him that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed her, if her father be vnwilling thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Sichem the Prince of Salem, did not thinke that he ſhould obteine the mariage of Dinah in ſpite of the teeth, or againſt the will of her parents, heareafter. Cap. 74.</p>
            <p>And becauſe that Muſculus doth refer the Reader, vnto that which he hath further writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vpon theſe words of Geneſis, concerning
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6202:37"/>this matter. <hi>And he brought her vnto him. &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe that this booke is in latine as the reſt of his workes, for the moſt part are, and for that euery one vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not this tongue, it ſhall not grieue me in this conſideration for the better ſatisfiyng of the godly Reader to turne that place vnto Engliſhe, where he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth after this manner.</p>
            <p>Here is to be noted, that God not only crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the woman,<note place="margin">That God himſelf bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the man, betrotheth her, &amp; ioineth her in mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age vnto him.</note> but alſo brought her vnto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eſpouſe and betroth her vnto him, and deliuered her &amp; ioyned her vnto him for his wife. She was made not onely of the fleſh and bones of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but alſo concerning kind, like vnto him in al thingss, as well as one beaſt is like vnto another beaſt of his kinde. Adam mought haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d her out without any great pain, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had found her, becauſe of her conformity or likenes vnto him, though diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring indeede in ſexe, yet acknowledge her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable vnto him in all other points, ioyn her vnto him, &amp; vſe her for the increaſing of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, like as wee ſee this to haue bene done by the beaſts, vnto none of the which we doe read, that this femal was brought ſeueraly. But god would not that either Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould do any of theſe things, vpon their own heads. Wherefore he himſelfe ioyned them together, &amp; brought the woman vnto Adam, deliuered and betrothed her being formed, &amp; made for lawful companie ſake. We are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by this conſideration, what lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6202:38"/>mariage doth require, namelie that the male and female or man and woman doe not ioine themſelues together vpon their ownt raſhneſſe &amp; luſt, but that they muſt be lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ioined together according vnto the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God by the aduiſe and will of their parentes and elders, whoſe partes in the ioining together of Adam &amp; Euah God too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon himſelfe. Such as are in this ſort ioined are ioined by God himſelfe, whoſe part and office the parentes and elders do rightlie and lawfullie ſupplie,<note place="margin">God ſupplied the part of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, when as he ioined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto Adam.</note> after the firſt ordinance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mariage vnder whoſe power and authorit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe that be ioined are. And in ſuch mariage that ſaying of Chriſt hath place. <hi>Whom God hath ioyned together, let no man put a ſunder.</hi> Thoſe that are ioyned together by bad practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by the wicked prouocation of luſt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of wealth, &amp; ſo foorth, without the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God cannot glorie of lawfull ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning together. It is further required, that we be not ioined after the maner of beaſtes, as ſhe by and by bee mine, which hauing the ſhape of a woman pleaſeth my luſt, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I take her to wife, the which is brought vnto me and deliuered by the Lord, &amp; that I may ſay of her: The woman which thou gaueſt me ô God, as in Chapiter following we reade to haue bene done by Adam. Therefore againſt this order are fornicators, whore maiſters, keepers of Concubines,<note place="margin">Which no wiſe ſtealer can doe.</note> and as many as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with a good conſcience glorie, that they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6202:38"/>haue their wiues lawfullie gotten.</p>
            <p>Peter Martyr in his commentarie vpon Geneſis,<note place="margin">Peter Marter vpon Geneſis Cap. 24. ver. 58.</note> ſpeaking of the betrothing and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſure of Rebeccah vnto Iſaac, writeth thus of the ſolemnities of that mariage: The ornamentes of this mariage were prayers, thankſgiuing, hoſpitalitie, the conſent of the maiden. For ſhe is not conſtrained, as it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten done by vngodlie parentes, who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times violentlie force husbandes vpon their daughters, or that which is worſe, doe thruſt them into Monaſteries or Abbeies. Nay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all thinges the conſent of the parentes doth here ſtep in betweene, whoſe office it is to beſtow their ſonnes or daughters in mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, neither is it their parts raſhlie to chooſe vnto themſelues wiues &amp;c. For I cite him the more ſparinglie, becauſe he hath written a learned common place of this argument, the which, although it be in engliſh, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (ſo far as I know) it is not to be had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerallie, but among the reſt of his common places, being a booke of too great a price for the poorer ſort, I haue bene the rather indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and mooued to labour alſo in this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that (as I truſt) not without ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite vnto the godlie diſpoſed, the which ſhall vouchſafe to read the ſame.</p>
            <p>Marlorat after he had ſaid ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the choiſe of a wife,<note place="margin">Marlorat.</note> the which Hagar made for her ſonne, at the laſt inferreth thus: Wherefore this youth (ſpeaking of Iſhmaell)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6202:39"/>being a man growen marrieth a wife, but not but by the counſaile &amp; authoritie of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and within a litle ſpace after: What then ought the children of the faithfull to perform vnto their parents? Doth it not beſeme and become them in making of mariage, to be led by the power and authority of their parents, that they giue not ouer themſelues vnto their owne luſtes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <note place="margin">Ferus a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh fryar.</note> To like purpoſe hath Ferus a Popiſh friar, noted vpon Abraham his pronouncing of a wife for Iſaac by his Steward. Theſe be his wordes: Note and marke, that Iſaac ſeeketh not a wife, but Abraham prouideth him of a wife. For this is the duty of parents, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth not properly vnto the ſonnes, whoſe part it is to obay.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <note place="margin">Borrhaus.</note> Borrhaus vpon the 22. of Exodus ver. 17 <hi>If the father of the maiden refuſeto giue her.</hi> A place for the power of parentes ouer their children in making of mariages, that theyr mariages do conſiſt in the arbitreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their parentes. Which thing Oreſtes in Euripides alloweth ſaiyng: And I will praiſe mariage, when as my father ſhal giue vnto me awife.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               <note place="margin">Bullinger. 1. Cor. 7 36.</note> Bullinger expounding theſe wordes of S. Paul in his Epiſtle vnto the Corinthians: <hi>But if he thinke it vnſeemely for his virgin &amp;c.</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on this ſort: Hee declareth by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that, which hee hath ſaide already, that there ſhould be no darknes in his words. And we may expound that word Virgin as wel for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6202:39"/>the perſon, as for the thing it ſelfe, namely virginity. The meaning is this, if a man haue a virgin marriable, and nowe ready for a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band (for this I vnderſtand by that which hee ſayeth, if ſhee paſſe the time of mariage, the which Ambroſe tranſlateth, if ſhe be paſt ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of age) and hath a deſire to mary (that is it which he ſaith, and ſo it ought to be) ſo that her father is to feare, leaſt that ſecretly ſhe go about, or enterpriſe ſome thing that is not comely, vnles ſhee be prouided for by mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, now the father ſinneth not, if hee beſtow her forth vpon an husband, &amp;c. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: we learne by this diſcourſe that it is the dutie of parents, to giue their daughters in mariage. For among them of old times, the contract of matrimony was not of any force,<note place="margin">Mariage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes void, without the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. nt of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes.</note> without the authority of the parents. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto that in the law of God ſemeth to apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn, the which is commaunded vnto the Iewes, that they ſhould not giue their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or theyr ſonnes vnto the Heathen in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: the which ſhould haue bin in vaine, if the children had bene at theyr owne liberty, and did not rather depend vpon the authority of their parents: yet this alſo muſt be added, that it is the part of parents in time conuenient to take order and prouide for their children, and that they compell them not either to virginity or ſingle life, or vnto mariage.</p>
            <p>Gualter is iuſt of the ſame iudgement vpon the very ſame place, whoſe words are:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiter.</note> But
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6202:40"/>here with all, ſonnes and daughters muſt mark that by this place the power of parentes ouer their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is eſtabliſhed, the which as it is great in other maters, ſo here in eſpecial hath it ſoueraigne authoritie, wheras the queſtion is concerning mariage. For if they muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for their children, in like maner it is their part to obey them, leaſt that by their luſt and head-ſtrong boldneſſe they doe preuent the aduiſe and pleaſure of their parentes For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ought the lawe of God to beare ſway with them, in the which they are commanded to haue their parentes in price and honour.<note place="margin">Num. 30.</note> And how great their authority is ouer their ſonnes and daughters it is manifeſt euen by this, that their parentes may diſanull and breake the vowes which their children haue made without their knowledge and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. When as therefore GOD himſelfe vouchſafeth to yeelde of his owne right, (that I may ſo ſpeake) and will not haue that ratified and ſtand, the which is promiſed vnto himſelfe, if the parentes determine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, they doubtleſſe are to be thought to bee too raſh and wicked, who will not ſubmit their youthfull deſires vnto the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and diſpoſing of their parentes. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may this goe for currant, that any ſhould pretend age for his excuſe. For there is no age the which ought to breake the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of parentes eſtabliſhed by the lawes of nature. And Paule in this place ſpeaketh of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6202:40"/>virgins, the which haue now alreadie paſſed the flower of their age, and mariage yeares, and neuertheleſſe ſubiecteth them alſo vnto the gouernment of their parents, when as he teacheth, not what they ought to doe, but what their parents ought to diſpoſe of them.<note place="margin">The ciuill lawes.</note> This in times paſt did the makers of the ciuil lawes deſerue, the which wold haue thoſe ma riages to be void, the which are made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the aduiſe and conſent of parents, vnleſſe ſome waightie caſe doe will them to be rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſtand in force.</p>
            <p>Agreeable vnto this alſo doeth Hemingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſet downe his iudgement vpon this place but in fewer wordes thus:<note place="margin">Hemingius.</note> Now he turneth his ſpeach vnto parentes hauing daughters of growen yeares, vnto whom he giueth autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to beſtowe their daughters in mariage if they will. But that which he putteth in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene (and ſo it ought to be) is a reſtraint, and it is to be vnderſtood thus; If the maiden be without the gift of chaſtitie it ought ſo to be: namelie that ſhe be giuen to be maried, to auoid fornication. On the other ſide if a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine haue the gift of chaſtitie, it is left free vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the parentes to marie them, and not to marie them. From hence let parents learne, that it is not lawfull for them, to lay vpon their children a perpetual law of chaſtitie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they be firſt ſure that they haue the gift of chaſtitie, the which verie ſeldome falleth out, vnles by ſome griefe or defect and want
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:6202:41"/>in nature.<note place="margin">Beza de repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis &amp; diuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lis.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beza in this caſe is ſo ſure on our ſide, that he holdeth not onely the ſtolen contracts to be void and vnlawfull, but alſo the mariage it ſelfe that followeth after the ſame to be of no force and vnlawfull But it is beſt to heare him tell his owne tale himſelfe. But what (ſaith hee) if mariage in deede haue followed after ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rracts? Doubtles if the cauſe be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered why ſuch contracts are vtterly void (be cauſe he namlie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not conſent to the beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himſelfe, the which is not in his owne power) it wil follow that the mariage it ſelfe ought much leſſe to bee of force, as verely wherin there is required a more expreſſe and ſure conſent.</p>
            <p>And Aretius in his common place of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage among other things that make the ſame vnlawfull rekoneth vp the contracting of the ſame without the conſent of parentes.<note place="margin">Aretius</note> His wordes be theſe: That mariage is vnlawful, the which is againſt the commandement and lawe of God. And this faulteth either in the degrees forbidden: or elſe becauſe it is made vp with priuie and ſtolen contractes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the will of the parentes: or els when as manie wiues are admitted or taken at one time.</p>
            <p>But we will conclude &amp; ſhut vp this point with the teſtimonie of M. Luther,<note place="margin">Luther.</note> the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolt of Germanie, whome wee haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued vnto this laſt place. not for that hee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6202:41"/>is the leaſt among my witneſſes, who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie ought to be accompted off euen with the verie foremoſt for his moſt profitable ſeruice done vnto the Church of GOD, but becauſe hee doeth verie euidentlie and clearelie with great courage and boldneſſe of heart ſet downe his iudgement in this cauſe writing vpon the 24. Chapiter of the booke of Geneſis: Therefore (ſaith hee) doe I handle this place, albeit odious or hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: Becauſe Iſaac doeth not marie a wife, where hee pleaſeth, but is forbidden of his father to marie one of the land of Canaan,<note place="margin">The miſchiefs the which do growe or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy contracts.</note> and his father himſelfe doeth carefullie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide his ſonne of a wife, and his ſonne with all willingneſſe doeth obey his father. For dailie experience doeth teach, that thoſe priuie and ſtolen contractes are the cauſe of great miſchiefes, daylie braules, ſtrifes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, and murthers, and alſo the moſt ſhamefull plague and garboile of the Church and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth. So the popiſh Canoniſts do nothing els but ſeek to teare in ſunder the Church and trouble the world becauſe of their doltiſh &amp; vnlearned Cannons. And ſhall wee ſuffer them to bring in ſo many miſchiefes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Churches? Let the Deuill winke at this, and no other man: nay rather I my ſelfe will excommunicate all thoſe doctors, then that we will to lerate and beare in our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches their wicked and vngodlie ſentences &amp; iudgement.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:6202:42"/>
            <p> And ſome prety ſpace after, he hath theſe wordes: The doctrine therefore of this place is, that parentes ought to prouide their ſons and daughters of honeſt mariage:<note place="margin">When pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do abuſe their authorltie.</note> Although this be not to be let paſſe, that it often times falleth out in mans life, that the parentes do ſometimes abuſe their power and authoritie, and will compel their children to marie with thoſe, whom they loue not, the which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth often to paſſe in the great families of noble men. They are to be found fault with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, becauſe they carie no ſparke of a fatherlie mind &amp; affection, but are blockes &amp; ſtockes, they haue not that ſame natural loue towards their children. In ſuch a caſe let the Paſtor of the Church, or the ciuil magiſtrate ſet in their authoritie Becauſe that this is not a father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie power, but a tyrannie. Wee therefore do ſo diligentlie vrge the authoritie of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, firſt becauſe of the commandement &amp; ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, the examples of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the ciuill lawes. Secondlie becauſe of that no table wickednes being vnto al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and honeſt parentes verie grieuous, the which hath raunged in the world in all ages: namelie that when as they haue brought vp their children godly and honeſtlie, that they might be heires of their fathers goodes, after wardes there haue bene ſome found they not knowing of it and againſt their willes,<note place="margin">The common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>actiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nongSt vs at his daie.</note> the which by diſceit and ſubtilty haue ouer-recht and compaſsed the maidens and honeſt yong
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6202:42"/>men, that they ſhoulde by ſtealth marie with thoſe, the which were both of ſmall honeſtie and alſo vnfit for them, and vnto their parents moſt vnwelcome.</p>
            <p>The Pope hath ſet open a window and a broad gate vnto theſe horrible offences,<note place="margin">The Pope gl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth leaue to ſteale away children from their parents.</note> and hath made a way for baudes, that they might ſteale away mens ſonnes and daughters for me, for thee, for euerie one of vs. Shall wee thinke theſe thinges to bee ſuffered, or defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? But they ſay that men muſt looke dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlie vnto the keeping of their children, &amp; haue an eſpeciall care of them: But how can this be inſo great wickednes and vntoward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of men? Howe eaſilie are the plaine and ſimple meaning mindes corrupted, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled?</p>
            <p>Let parents therfore remember that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and authoritie is giuen them from God to beſtow their children in mariage:<note place="margin">Contractes uoid without the conſent of parents.</note> and that contractes made without their conſent are not good, neither by the lawe of God nor man.</p>
            <p>Furthermore let children knowe that they are to aske their aduiſe and to knowe their pleaſure. Let not a yoong man,<note place="margin">A graue co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſell vnto al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> honeſt your<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whoſe age is fit for mariage, be afraid to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mind vnto his parents: that he is in loue with an honeſt maiden, and deſire, that they will geue her him to wife. For albeit this ſeeme to be a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of luſt ſcarce comelie, yet let them know that God his mercy doth couer the ſame in
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6202:43"/>mariage, &amp; hath giuen a remedie for this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. Let them therfore humble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their parentes, and plainelie and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſay vnto them: my deare father, my good mother, giue me ſuch a yoong man, or ſuch a maiden, whome I loue. And if ſhe be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be matched with thee, or worthie of thine affinitie, or thy parentes, thine honeſt parentes will not denie thee, albeit the dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie or wealth bee not anſwerable. Such mariages cannot chooſe but bee happie and proſperous,<note place="margin">God doth co uer &amp; beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy luſt with neſt mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age.</note> and God of his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe dooth bleſſe, pardon, and couer the heat of luſt as it were with the couer of mariage. Yea, more ouer the holie ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture dooth allowe, and alleadge for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the loue and ſpeach of the bridegroome and bride. Thus God pardonneth the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, and miſerable luſt, wherein wee are borne, and that which more is, dooth beautifie and honeſt the ſame with lawfull mariage. But let yoong men take heede and beware of this vſuall ſtubbornneſſe and contempt of parentes, wherewithall ſome run ſtarke mad, &amp; of a blind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age do contract vnhoneſt mariages, vnfitting both themſelues &amp; alſo their elders &amp; pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. For in this place the holy ſcripture ſetteth forth a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and far more honeſt, to be followed, when as Iſaac marieth Rebeccah, according vnto the minde, will and counſail, of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:6202:43"/>
            <p> Theſe thinges thus conſidered, and this matter ſo generallie agreed vpon, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med alſo by the approbation and conſent of ſo manie graue, godlie, and learned witneſſes, if hen ceforward the pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſhal either of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence or ſluggiſhneſſe leaue of their dutie in prouiding of honeſt matches for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or their ſonnes and daughters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſlie and ſtubbornlie refuſe to ſtand vnto their godlie and chriſtian choiſe, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance will no longer ſerue to excuſe the fault on either ſide, but that it muſt needes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that the ſeruant that knoweth his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters wil, and dooth it not,<note place="margin">A neceſsatie aduiſe vnto parents.</note> the ſame ſhall bee beaten with many ſtripes. Let fathers therfore on whom the charge by God his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lieth to take wiues for their ſons, and to prouide husbandes for their daughters, take dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t heed herunto, that they abuſe not this their power and authoritie ouer their children, but as in other caſes, they are willed by the Apoſtle that they deal not in ſuch ſort to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them, that they hereby bee diſmaied and diſcouraged, ſo eſpeciallie in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of greateſt moment and valour of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worldelie thinges whatſoeuer, let them abſteine from all rigour and roughneſſe,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.22.</note> and beware that they turne not their fatherlie iuriſdiction and gouernment into a tyranm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſowerneſſe and way wardneſſe, letting their will goe for a lawe and their pleaſure for a reaſon, according vnto that olde,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6202:44"/>but both Tiger and Tirant lyke ſaying: Looke what I commaund, that will I haue, my wil ſtandeth for a reaſon. For the rule of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes ouer theyr children, ought to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the gouernment of good princes towards their ſubiects, that is to ſay, it muſt be milde, gentle, and eaſie to be borne, for as they, ſo like wiſe parents ſo far as concerneth them and lieth in theyr abilitie to performe, they muſt carrie ſuch an euen and vpright hand in their gouernement,<note place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lie in the ſecond book of office.</note> that they may by loue ſeeke to win the hartes of thoſe ouer whome they are ſet, to bee firme and ſure to wardes them, and not to keepe them vnder awe and ſubiection by feare. For, whom men feare, they hate, and him whom they hate, his death they wiſhe. I ſpeake of ſeruile or ſlauiſhe fear, not of that child-like and reuerent feare, the which both the ſubiects owe vnto their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the children vnto their parents, and the which both the one and the other eaſilie obtaine at the handes of ſuch as are vnder their gouernment, by their equal, vpright and moderate behauiour towardes them.</p>
            <p>It doth therefore ſtand parentes greatly in hand,<note place="margin">Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ought to deale ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely in the choife for their children</note> that in making choiſe for their children they be free from all ſiniſter and corrupt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and that for lucre &amp; couetouſnes they ſeeke not to thruſt ſuch matches vpon their children, as they cannot brooke, nor like well off: for now adaies in the choiſe that a great manie parentes make of husbandes for their
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6202:44"/>daughters, and wiues for their ſonnes, <hi>Et ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus &amp; forma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Regina pecunia donat:</hi> that is, if they bee ritch inough, they be both faire, wel fauoured, yea and alſo godlie and vertuous inough: they being farre ſwarued from the mind &amp; iudgement of that father, who once ſaid concerning the mariage of his daughter, that he had rather haue a man without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, then money without a man: ſignifieng hereby that he rather reſpected the good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and vertues of his minde, then the great wealth and ritches of his cofers. Fathers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as they are by good right to chooſe, ſo ought they not in truth to conſtraine &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel For of al other matters, the conſent of the children in mariage ought to be moſt free, ſo that in theſe caſes, after all honeſt and lawful perſwaſions vſed, looke in what partie the fault may be worthelie thought to reſt, there the godly magiſtrate ought to put in his foot,<note place="margin">The godlie magiſtrate.</note> who in ſome reſpectes is not onelie in the ſcriptures comprehended vnder the name of a father, but alſo by his ſoueraigne au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thoritie wherewithall hee is armed from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, is to rule both the father and all his children, and all other, that doe belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. I am not able, neither is it my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to reckon all the colourable pretenſes that fathers which are worldlie minded can alleadge to enforce vpon their children what yokefellowes ſoeuer they haue procured and prouided for them, ſo that they bee rich
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6202:45"/>inough: neither yet is it poſsible for mee to ſet down all the ſhiftes, that children haue to ſhake off the yoke of due obedience in their fathers honeſt and lawfull choiſes. This therefore in all humilitie, euen in the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of leſus Chriſt I requeſt at the handes of them both, that they ſeeke not how to bee wiſe and wittie (or rather in deed) wilie how to deuiſe windleſſes and ſtarting holes to ſhrowde and hide themſelues in, when they ſhould perfourme their duties on either part in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>The children can ſay for themſelues, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are olde enough,<note place="margin">The plea of ſome childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> king of their own matches.</note> and therefore able enough to make our own choiſe: we ſee it to be dayly practiſed by others, yea and peraduenture w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doe know (as hauing hard our parents ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in their merrimentes to bragge of the ſame) our fathers haue matched without the conſent of their parentes, and haue all this notwithſtanding done well ynough, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued verie well: why therefore ſhoulde not wee alſo doo the like? The queſtion here is not,<note place="margin">The reply.</note> what children in regarde either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> age or wit are able for to doo but what God hath thought meet &amp; exped e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nay, ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie charged and commanded that they ſhould doe. For there are many children found ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times far to exceede their fathers in wit and in wiſedome, yea and in al other giſes both of mind &amp; body, yet is this no good reaſon that they ſhould take vpon them their fathers an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6202:45"/>The wife may not therfore be a mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, becauſe ſhe hath more knowledge ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times then her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but ſhe muſt obey, &amp; the husbande is to rule, becauſe that God hath willed that it ſhould bee ſo. And albeit that matches made without the conſent of parentes haue often good ſucceſſe, accro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the things which fal out outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in this life, yet that is not to bee imputed vnto this diſordered and vnnaturall courſe, but vnto God his mercie that alwaies dooth better for vs, then wee haue deſerued. And whereas it is ſaid, that our parents haue mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched without the choiſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, therfore we alſo wil chooſe for ourſelues according vnto our owne liking, beſides that the breach of dutie in the father doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the like diſobedience in his ſonne:<note place="margin">A bad ſonne, that wil haue his father go with him vnto the deuil for companie.</note> what art thou that thinkeſt it not inough that thou goe vnto the Deuill thy ſelfe vnleſſe thou haue thy father to go with thee alſo for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie? For as thy ſin of diſobedience, if God graunt thee not repentance of the ſame, ſhall in his iuſtice preſſe thee down euen vnto hel. So likewiſe ſhall thy fathers marieng without the allowance of his parents, be ſufficient to condemne him, if together with the reſt of his ſinnes it bee not couered in the merites of Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour. And the example of Iudah may fitlie ſerue to inſtruct thee in this point, that though thy father haue maried without the choiſe of his friendes,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6202:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:6202:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:6202:47"/>yet thou art not in like maner to marie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of them,<note place="margin">Gen. 38.</note> for albeit Iudah tooke vnto himſelfe a Cananitiſh woman without the priuitie and liking of his father Iaacob, yet did hee prouide a wife for his owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Er, and Onan, whereby wee gather that the fault, the which hee committed in himſelfe, hee did not like nor allow of in his ſonnes.</p>
            <p>Setting a ſide therefore all cunning glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and colourable deuiſes hammered in the Deuill his forge,<note place="margin">A profitable counſaile for all good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> whereby hee teacheth his ſchollers to be ſubtile in inuenting reaſons to maintaine their ſtubborne diſobedience in not being ruled by the graue aduiſe &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie counſaile of their parentes as touching their mariage matches, let all dutifull and good natured children in the reuerence and feare of God conſider what honour and obedience they doe owe vnto their parents and what power and authoritie he hath in his worde ſanctified vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer their children in the Lord, in regard hereof let them yeeld, vnto them this dutie, that their fathers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing prouided for them ſuch as are not of a wicked life, nor deformed or euill fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nor of a contrarie religion, they wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie ſubmit themſelues vnto their choiſe, which if for the preſent, or vpon the ſuddain they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not yeeld vnto, let them by earneſt cal ling vpon the name of God deſire him to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due in them this corrupt affection &amp; that he
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6202:47"/>will frame their wil to bee plyable vnto their fathers in ſuch lawful caſes: lawful I may well call them, becauſe that the ciuil conſtitutions and ordinances do ratifie and allow of them: the two former eſpeciallie, ſetting downe that children are to giue the conſent vnto the fathers choiſe, where the partie choſen is not of infamous life,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14.</note> nor in ſhape or fauour ſo blemiſhed, as it may worthelie bee ſuppoſed that the ſame may be an occaſion of the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawiug of loue As for the third caution, or prouiſo of not gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting vnto the fathers choiſe in the cauſe of contrarie religion, it is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med flatlie by the counſell of the Apoſtle, where he willeth that we ſhould not draw the yoke with infidels, which if it hold in other caſes of the affaires of this life, much more ought it to bee of force in mariage matters, mariage (I meane) hereafter to bee made and not ſuch as are alreadie made, for where the knot is once already knit, there diſparitie, or vnequalnes in religion is no iuſt cauſe of ſeperation.</p>
            <p>Yea &amp; in this moſt graue &amp; waighty cauſe,<note place="margin">In prouiding of watches for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntes ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> I would be author vnto all chriſtian parentes that they take not the ſame lightly in hand as if it were but a toy, or a ieſt, but that they begin it with praier that in the whole actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they may in ſuch ſort be directed, that they do nothing againſt the word of God, or vnbeſeeming the ſame authority, the which God himſelf in this cauſe hath impoſed or laid vpon them. And
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6202:48"/>thus doing, God no doubt will ad a bleſsing vnto their godlie indeuour and holie care, &amp; worke obedience in the heartes of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as hee framed the heart of Iſaac with entire affection to imbrace Rebeccah, whom his father Abraham had by his Steward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for him. And leaſt that any ſhould ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that this counſell is a pecuiſh fancie of a too much ſpiced and nice conſcience, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ought to bee induced and perſwaded hereunto,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.7. Aben Ezra holdeth this to haue bene a praier.</note> firſt by the example of Abraham, who committing the charge of prouiding a wife for his ſonne vnto his ſeruant, praieth that God will ſend his Angell before him to direct him in this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondlie the courſe which Abraham his ſeruant taketh in the effecting of this charge dooth teach no leſſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.12.</note> of whom we reade, that he entred into this buſineſſe with praier:<note place="margin">Gen. 24.26.</note> that he geueth thankes vnto God, when hee mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with Rebeccah:<note place="margin">Gen. 24.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that hee praiſeth God when at the deliuerie of his meſſage, the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes without gaine-ſaieng graunted their conſent.</p>
            <p>And whileſt I giue this counſell vnto the parentes,<note place="margin">Children ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-able are to pray vnto God to direct their parentes in a godly choiſe, and to incline their mindes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the ſame.</note> I woulde not haue the children thinke that I diſcharge them of this dutie, of whom the ſame is by ſo much the more to be put in practiſe, by how much they are more ſubiect to bee caried away with the ſwift current of their ſtay-leſſe affections, from whome wee heare too often theſe and ſuch
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6202:48"/>like more then prophane and heatheniſh ſpeaches': <hi>I will marie to pleaſe mine owne eie, and not to ſatisfie the mind of my father: I will neuer match with him that woeth my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents before he woeth me: Shal I go to the father before I am ſure of the daughter. &amp;c.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in verie deede they are not at all once ſo much as to make the leaſt motion of mariage vnto the daughter, vnleſſe before they, haue obtained the good will and liking of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For in theſe caſes let the daughters, if they ſhall be thereunto ſollicited and woed, learne of the example of the maiden out of the Poet, and of Cyrus out of Xenophon ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, to ſay vnto their ſuters: My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and my mother haue to determine and diſpoſe of my mariage, this is a matter not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing nor appertaining vnto me. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then haue borne themſelues in this dutifull ſort towardes their parentes, and ſhall I that profeſſe my ſelfe a chriſtian come ſo far ſhort of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this dutie, as to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract my ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent &amp; knowledge of my elders? Nay let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay with Tamar, as it is in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the kings: <hi>Speake I pray thee vnto my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for he will not deny me vnto thee. &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13 verſe. 13</note>
            </p>
            <p>And here, when as I enter into the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the contrarie bad courſe &amp; practiſe of the world, in intiſing of mens ſonnes and daughters vnto mariage without,<note place="margin">Againſt inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto mariage without the conſent of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</note> nay againſt the conſent and will of their parents, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me aſtoniſhed and amazed, to heare that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6202:49"/>a great manie, and the ſame otherwiſe verie ciuill and honeſt, are to be found almoſt in all places, the which not onelie doe not diſlike of this ſhamefull diſorder, but holde it as it were but a ſport and a play, yea that which more is, goe about to countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and defend this notorious kind of ſhameleſſe theeuerie, (for ſo I will not feare to call it) the which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo doth farre better deſerue to bee puniſhed with death, then a great manie crimes that are puniſhed with the ſame. Yea thou thy ſelfe which likeſt hereof wel enough &amp; too well, if a theefe take but xx. ſhillings ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee by the highway ſide, thou wilt hang him, if thou can: &amp; art thou ſo bad an eſteemer of thinges, that thou doeſt value the ſtealing away of a mans childe at a leſſe rate, then the taking away of his mony? Wilt thou condemn him that ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth away thy beaſt, and iuſtify him that rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth thee of thy daughter?<note place="margin">Deut. 24 7.</note> The law of God ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pointeth death vnto ſuch as ſteale mens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into ſlauery of the bodie, &amp; what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinkeſt thou is their offence which ſteale mens daughters againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, to liue all their life time in whordome &amp; adulterie, which is a ſpirituall ſlauerie and bondage of the ſoule, by which without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance it periſheth euerlaſtingly, whereas the bodily bondage nothing preiudicateth or hindereth the libertie of the ſoule, but that it notwithſtanding may bee a free man vnto Chriſt? If theft by the conſent, and iudgement
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6202:49"/>of all the learned be truly defined, and ſaid, to be the taking away and withholding of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man his goodes, againſt the will of the owner of the ſame: and children, as hath bin before proued, be by good right to be reko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eſpecially among the ſubſtance of theyr parentes: how then, is it not theft to ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way mens childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by intiſing them vnto ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage? And this argueth a great prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our time, and a wonderfull growth, and increaſe of ſinne vnto his higheſt toppe, that whereas all other theeues for the moſte part either ſteale in the night, or elſe diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and vizarded in the day time, keeping themſelues ſecret and hidden leaſt being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, they ſtretch a rope for their labour: the ſtealers of our daughters ſometimes will not ſticke to tell vs to our faces, that if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not obtaine them with our good will,<note place="margin">Shameles boldnes.</note> they will if they can by any means, one day enioy them in deſpite of our teeth. And when they haue once atchieued their deuiliſhe purpoſe, and offered villany vnto our children, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing of their bodies, they do not as other theeues, keepe themſelues aloofe and creepe into corners, but offer themſelues willingly inough to be knowne, making within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues this reckoning, and ſometimes openly vaunting hereof among their friendes, that hauing thus diſhoneſted our children, we ſhal in the end be glad to make ſute vnto them to keepe them, for feare leaſt like vnto graceles
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6202:50"/>Amnon, they ſhould turne them thus abuſed, home againe vnto vs.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.15.</note> This is the daily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and yet who almoſt is ſory for the ſame? But if there bee no man nor woman to bee found, hauing any ſparke of conſcience left vnquenched, but confeſſeth, that hee would not haue his own ſonne and daughter intiſed after this manner, let vs not then any longer goe about to vpholde, that done vnto others, the which we would diſſalow and greatly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like being done vnto our ſelues, and in our owne caſes For this rule ſhall otherwiſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill in force inough againſt vs: Doe not vnto another, that which thou wouldeſt be loth ſhould be done vnto thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>An obiection of maid-ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</label> But it may be aunſwered hereunto, not by the Sheepe-ſtealers, but by the maide ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, that they haue the conſent and goodwill of the maiden, and that peraduenture ſo far forth, that ſhe hath in moſt earneſt maner, yea euen with teares, and for all the loue ſake that euer was betweene them, made requeſt and ſute vnto them to carie and conueigh her away, and by ſome ſecret meanes to bee married vnto them &amp;c. <label>Anſwer.</label> This is indeede a verye plauſible couloure, and ſuch as carrieth a greate ſhewe of reaſon among many, but is in trueth the very worſt plea that they could poſſibly haue made for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of all others. For doe they not ſee, how by this meanes they doe not alone quite caſt and cleane ouerthrowe themſelues, but
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6202:50"/>alſo accuſe and condemne the party, whom they haue after this ſort ſeduced and intiſed? For beſides theyr owne fault in going about this matter without the conſent of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, (the which as hath bene ſhewed ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently already, they ought like good children to haue taried for) they haue cauſed the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den alſo, to caſt off and breake in ſunder the coardes of due obedience vnto her father or mother, which greate contempt, the Lorde wil not ſuffer vnreuenged. And becauſe that ſuch maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracts are altogether by God his word vnlawful, therfore in carnaly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the one the other (the which for the moſte parte is the beſt end of theſe bad compactes) they haue committed fornication, heaping as it were drunkeneſſe vnto thirſte, that is to ſay, committing one ſinne in the necke of another, the which may not hereby be excuſed, for that they haue plighted and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed their fayth and troth the one vnto the other, and therefore they cannot in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence forſake one another.<note place="margin">That the vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; promiſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which childr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> make to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the one vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the other, without the conſent of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> parents is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> matter of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcience, and may lawful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be broken.</note> For it muſt firſt be conſidered, whether theyr vow and promiſe bee lawfull or no, before they enter into a ſetled determination, to performe and keepe the ſame. For where the vowe is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, there can be no breach of conſcience in obſeruing and fulfilling the ſame. And as in all other caſes, and actions of ours, the worde of GOD muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e bee our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, to trye the lawfulnes, or vnlawfulnes,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6202:51"/>of the ſame, ſo alſo in this moſt chiefly, when wee vowe or promiſe by giuing our ſayth, to doe any thing in his name. For nothing can pleaſe God, the which is not agreeable vnto his will, and we haue no other certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate left vs to aſſure vs of his will, but onely his worde. Wherefore whatſoeuer cannot be warranted by the ſame, is not agreable vnto his wil, and ſo conſequently can by no means pleaſe him. Let vs then ſee a little, whether this vowing and giuing of fayth and troth in mariage, without the parents agreeing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, be to be holden lawfull, yea, or no, the which ſhall eaſely appeare vnto vs thus: what ſoeuer cannot bee performed, without the breache of God his commaundement, that ſame is vtterlye vnlawfull to be done, but to vow faith and troth in mariage, without the conſent of parents, can not bee performed without the breach of God his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, therefore for children to giue their fayth and troth in mariage, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of theyr parentes, is vtterly vnlawfull. As concerning vowes God teacheth vs in the 30. of Numbers that being made by the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and not ratified by the parents, they are vnlawfull, and if vnlawfull not to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med And that it is againſt God his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, for children to handfaſt themſelues in wedlocke, their parents conſent not going there withall, hath at large bene diſcourſed, being the only matter of this Treatize, wherof
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:6202:51"/>enſueth, that theſe promiſes being vnlawful, they do not at all binde the conſcience of the makers of them to performe the ſame, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the perfourming of them, is a matter not of conſcience, but flat againſt conſcience, if to do the thing that is vnlawfull, and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by the word of God, be a matter againſt conſcience, the which none, vnles the face be made of ſeaſoned wainſcot, will eaſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. Let not thoſe therefore the which plead conſcience for theyr excuſe in this bad mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, any longer deceiue themſelues with this broken reede, the which, if one leane vpon, it will ſtraight wayes breake vnto ſhiuers,<note place="margin">An vnlawful vowe or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe may laws fully bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> but rather whoſoeuer haue in this ſort vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or promiſed raſhly, let them vnderſtand, that their vowe and promiſe, may a greate deale more ſafely be broken, then performed, except the good will of the parents may bee obtayned, and yet in this caſe alſo, their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer raſhnes is earneſtly and with vnfained and hearty ſorrow to be repented, that God through his mercy in Chriſt doe not impute it and lay it vnto their charge. And this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe I would haue to be vnderſtoode either of contractes, or of mariage alſo by ſuch inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing meanes, though the parents good will may be afterwads procured. But if after ſuch priuy and ſtolen contracts and mariages, the good liking of the parentes cannot be won, what puniſhment ought to be inflicted and laid vpon the offenders, as well in regard of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:6202:52"/>their owne default in breach of duty vnto their parentes, as alſo that others by their ſmart may bee terrified and feared from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into the like, it is not for mee being no lawe-maker to determine: I leaue that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wiſe diſcretion of the godly magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, who I hope heareafter wil cary a more heauy hande towardes this he nous and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius crime, and ſee ſome diſcipline alſo to bee ordained for all ſuch diſobedient and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly children, the which by their raſhe and headſtrong attentes, haue forſtalled the right of their godly parents, howſoeuer afterwards they can get their good will.</p>
            <p>And thus,<note place="margin">The concluſion.</note> ſith the law of nature, the lawe of God, the authority of the ſcriptures, the examples of the godlye recorded in the ſame, the practiſe of the better ſort, among the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heathen, the teſtimonyes of the Poettes in their Comedies, and Tragedies, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Councels, Decrees, Canons, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conſtitutions of the purer ſort, yea ſome of the very Popes themſelues, and laſtly the firme conſent of the beſt Diuines of theſe our dayes, maintaine and vpholde the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes right in prouiding of honeſt matches in due time for their children, and prooue their contractes made without their parents conſent, to bee of no validity or force, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before God or man: I may lawfullye conclude, that it is the fathers charge to make a godlye choiſe, for his ſonnes and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:6202:52"/>daughters in the way of mariage, without whoſe conſent they are at no hand to knit vp the ſame, vnleſſe the godlie magiſtrate in caſes of extremitie by his authoritie doe take ſuch order, ſo that hereafter my good hope is (the duties on both ſides being nowe ſo plainelie ſet downe, that no ignorance in this behalfe may any longer hencefoorth be pretended) that as parents reſpecting God his glorie, wil diligentlie and carefullie practiſe the one, ſo their children in all humble obedience will peforme the other, which God grant at the length for Chriſt his ſake.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="afterword">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:6202:53"/>
            <head>An afterwritte to the gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y purpoſe was (right gentle Reader) in this ſhort diſcourſe before going, by ſtrong and ſounde proues to make this point of doctrine appeare moſt clearely, the which of the moſte hath neuer bin ſo much as once thought vpon, and whereof a greate number, very ſenſible men otherwiſe, haue hitherto bin of this perſwaſion, that the word of God, ſpeaketh not at all, namely of this duty of the parentes in making choiſe for theyr childrens mariage, or of the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the which the ſonnes and daughters in this reſpect do owe, vnto the godly choiſe of their fathers and mothers in this ſo holy an action.</p>
            <p>How I haue performed the ſame, I leaue vnto the iudgement of the indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, vpon the conſiderations of the reaſons and authorities by me alleaged, in the which my chiefe end and drift was, to ſatisfie the godly and wel diſpoſed Chriſtians, the which will make ſome care of conſcience to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that hereafter, the which hitherto of ignorance and want of inſtruction, they haue
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:6202:53"/>neglected and omitted. For when as parents ſhall hencefoorth plainelie ſee,<note place="margin">Parentes.</note> that God himſelfe layeth vpon them this neceſsarie duetie of beſtowing their children honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and godlie in wedlocke: and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren euidentlie nowe perceiue that they ought to ſtand vnto the godlie choiſe of their parentes, thoſe in whoſe heartes the feare of God is not vtterlie quenched, will hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward indeuour themſelues to yeeld obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto their ſuperiours in this moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsarie and waightie dutie,<note place="margin">Children.</note> with all willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being contented to bee ruled, and not to ſeeke rule, nor to intrude and thruſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into the right and libertie of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, vpon whom the Lord in his wiſdome hath laide his charge, ſo that without their priuitie and conſent, they will not intangle themſelues in mariage, nor ſeeke vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues matches, ſuch as may bee griefes and eie-fores vnto their louing Parentes, vnto whome in the Lorde they worthelie owe all obedience and dutifull ſubiection. I ſpeake here of the godlie and better ſort both of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes and alſo children, who beeing of the people and Church of God, will be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and ruled by the lawes and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the which hee himſelfe hath ſet downe for the direction and gouernment of the ſame in all other their waies and actions. As for the wicked and vngodlie, which rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liouſlie thinke in their hearts and ſometimes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:6202:54"/>blaſphemouſlie vtter with their mouthes: <hi>Let vs breake his bandes and caſt his cordes from vs.</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note> will not ſuffer God to raign ouer them after ſuch manner as he hath appointed in his word, I make ſmall account or reckoning of their either liking or diſliking of this my ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple labour, but refer them ouer vnto him that dwelleth in heauen, &amp; laugheth at them and ſhall haue them in deriſion. But vnto all you that either be in trueth Chriſtians, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe would ſo be taken and accounted, know you that this cuſtome of the parentes placing and beſtowing their children in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, is as hath bene ſhewed, moſt ancient, and comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable, yea and approoued by our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt himſelfe alſo in the xx of Luke,<note place="margin">Luk, 20.11.</note> where, going about to confute the errour of the Saduces, the which, if there were a reſurrection (which they denie) did ſuppoſe that there muſt be alſo mariage, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoucheth it to haue bene the ordinarie pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the men of thoſe times to giue their children to be maried: ſaieng, <hi>The children of this world mary wiues, and are giuen or beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in mariage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th to place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beſtow in marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they giue their children to be married</note> for ſo doeth the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in that place hee vſeth, moſt properlie in the iudgment of the learned ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie. And by the men of this world, as well the wicked as the godly, leaſt that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wee might thinke that mariage dooth not appertaine vnto the children of God if we ſhould here take children of this world
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:6202:54"/>as oppoſite and ſette againſt the children of light, or of God, as I confeſſe it muſt ſome times bee taken, which in this place cannot be leaſte it might ſeeme to giue ſome coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce vnto the error before recited. So that hereby clearely appeareth, that in the dayes of Chriſt 1589, yeares ſithens and more, this was an order generally obſerued, for the parentes in mariage to place and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe their children, the which alſo Beza,<note place="margin">Beza ſaith that this place moſt ſtrongly proueth the power &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing their children in mariage.</note> and Feguernekinus, who hath profitably a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged Marlorat his common places, doth note vpon this place. Let not Chriſtians therfore diſlike of that, which Chriſt himſelfe, after whom they are named, ſeemeth to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend. But let them rather, knowing what God looketh for at their handes, in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon prouide wiues for their ſonnes, and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes for their daughters, leaſt by forſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time too long, they bee either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by their childrens to raſh contracting themſelues, or otherwiſe to their greater ſorrowe, ſee them runne into more greater folly, as it often commeth to paſſe, when as the ſonnes and daughters, think that their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers haue no care of them in this behalfe, yea in this buſines let them carrie ſo gentle an hand towarde their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that they themſelues feeling beſt their owne eſtate, when as they be come vnto years and diſcretion conuenient, may, if their child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly modeſty will ſuffer them deale with their
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:6202:55"/>parentes concerning this matter in an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and reuerend manner by themſelues, or otherwiſe by the godly intercesſion of their friendes, who at their motion may put their parentes in minde, in time conuenient to haue care of theſe caſes, by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, many inconueniences and diſorders ſhal bee met with ill before hand, the which for want of this Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foreſight on both ſides, do too vſually fall out, to the diſhonour of God, and offence of his Church The end of all is, that both the parentes and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, vnderſtanding what God looketh for on both their partes in this buſines, ſet aſide all caueling and cunning gloſes to ſhake of this dutie. For I will not trouble my ſelfe wyth aunſwering theſe many and vaine obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions on this behalfe, vſuall to bee alleaged on both ſides, but refer them ouer vnto the thorow ſhifting of their ſeuerall conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in theſe actions, according vnto that, the which by this treatiſe, they ſhall learne to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine vnto their ſeuerall duties, that they may in ſincerity and truth effect the ſame, being deſirous, as purpoſedly to offend none, ſo gladly in this point to ſatiffie al, the which if it be not alrea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy performed accordingly, ſo far as the queſtion taken in hand, to proue requireth, I will endeuour, as I ſhall heareaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by any the godly be aduertiſed, and labour (God willing) more fully and largely (ſo far as in me lieth) to ſet downe, to the full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:6202:55"/>of all ſuch as are not purpoſedlye reſolued and determined, in this cauſe to cauill, thwartle, and diſſemble, hoping that the godly ſhall profite, to the perfourming of a neceſſary dutie, yet of a great parte left vnperfourmed, and the wicked bee made vnexcuſeles, when the accounts muſt be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, before that iudge, which ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l geue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence without regarde of the perſon of any whatſoeuer, that ſhall coulorably ſeeke to withdraw his necke out of his lawful and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull obedience. Wherefore in this duty, or any other, the which the warrant of God his word may iuſtifie, howſoeuer the ſame in any reſpect may ſeeme ſtrange vnto vs, let it bee our continuall and moſt earneſt praier, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God to ſubdue our corrupt and carnall affections vnto his moſt holie will, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie pleaſure, ſo far foorth as we ſhall haue his word the infallible lode-ſtone to direct and guide vs vnto the ſame, for Chriſt his ſake. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:56"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by Iohn Wolfe for Iohn Hariſon the yoonger, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in Paternoſter-row, at the ſigne of the golden Ancher. 1589.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6202:56"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
